^ (Pss. 60:0-68:35) To the director; set to “The Lily of Reminder.” Mikʹtam.* Of David. For teaching. When he fought with Aʹram-na·ha·raʹim and Aʹram-Zoʹbah, and Joʹab returned and struck down 12,000 Eʹdom·ites in the Valley of Salt. 60 O God, you rejected us; you broke through our defenses. You were angry with us; but now accept us back!  2 You caused the earth to quake; you split it open. Repair its breaches, for it is falling.  3 You caused your people to suffer hardship. You made us drink wine that makes us stagger.  4 Give* a signal to those fearing you To flee and dodge the bow. (Selah)  5 So that your loved ones may be rescued, Save us with your right hand and answer us.  6 God has spoken in his holiness:* “I will exult, I will give out Sheʹchem as an inheritance, And I will measure off the Valley* of Sucʹcoth.  7 Gilʹe·ad belongs to me, as does Ma·nasʹseh, And Eʹphra·im is the helmet* for my head; Judah is my commander’s staff.  8 Moʹab is my washbasin. Over Eʹdom I will throw my sandal. Over Phi·lisʹti·a I will shout in triumph.”  9 Who will bring me to the besieged* city? Who will lead me as far as Eʹdom? 10 Is it not you, O God, who have rejected us, Our God, who no longer goes out with our armies? 11 Help us in our distress, For salvation by humans is worthless. 12 By God we will gain power, And he will trample on our adversaries.

To the director; to be accompanied with stringed instruments. Of David. 61 Hear, O God, my cry for help. Do pay attention to my prayer.  2 From the ends of the earth I will cry out to you When my heart is in despair.* Lead me onto a rock that is higher than I am.  3 For you are my refuge, A strong tower that protects me from the enemy.  4 I will be a guest in your tent forever; I will take refuge in the shelter of your wings. (Selah)  5 For you, O God, have heard my vows. You have given me the inheritance belonging to those who fear your name.  6 You will add days to the life* of the king, And his years will be from generation to generation.  7 He will sit enthroned* forever before God; Grant him* loyal love and faithfulness, so that these may safeguard him.  8 Then I will sing praises* to your name forever As I pay my vows day after day.

To the director; of Je·duʹthun.* A melody of David. 62 Indeed, I wait* silently for God. My salvation comes from him.  2 Indeed, he is my rock and my salvation, my secure refuge;* I will never be greatly shaken.  3 How long will you assault a man in order to murder him? All of you are as dangerous as a leaning wall, a stone wall ready to collapse.*  4 For they consult together to topple him from his high position;* They take pleasure in lying. With their mouth they bless, but inside they are cursing. (Selah)  5 Indeed, I wait silently* for God Because my hope comes from him.  6 Indeed, he is my rock and my salvation, my secure refuge; I will never be shaken.  7 Upon God depends my salvation and my glory. My strong rock, my refuge, is God.  8 Trust in him at all times, O people. Pour out your hearts before him. God is a refuge for us. (Selah)  9 The sons of men are a mere breath, The sons of mankind are a delusion. When laid together on the scales, they are lighter than a mere breath. 10 Do not trust in extortion Or put false hopes in robbery. If your wealth increases, do not set your heart on it. 11 Once God has spoken, twice I have heard this: That strength belongs to God. 12 Also loyal love is yours, O Jehovah, For you repay each one according to his deeds.

A melody of David, when he was in the wilderness of Judah. 63 O God, you are my God, I keep looking for you. I do thirst* for you. I am* faint with longing for you In a dry and parched land, where there is no water.  2 So I have looked upon you in the holy place; I have seen your strength and your glory.  3 Because your loyal love is better than life, My own lips will glorify you.  4 Thus I will praise you all my life; In your name I will lift up my hands.  5 I am* satisfied with the best and choicest portion,* So my mouth will praise you with joy on my lips.  6 I remember you while upon my bed; I meditate on you during the watches of the night.  7 For you are my helper, And I shout joyfully in the shadow of your wings.  8 I cling* to you; Your right hand keeps fast hold on me.  9 But those who seek to destroy my life* Will descend into the depths of the earth. 10 They will be handed over to the power of the sword; They will become food for jackals.* 11 But the king will rejoice in God. Every person swearing by Him will exult,* For the mouth of those speaking lies will be silenced.

To the director. A melody of David. 64 Hear my voice, O God, as I plead. Safeguard my life from the dreadfulness of the enemy.  2 Shield me from the secret plots of wicked men, From the crowd of wrongdoers.  3 They sharpen their tongue just like a sword; They aim their cruel words like arrows,  4 To shoot at the innocent from their hiding places; They shoot at him suddenly, without fear.  5 They hold fast to their evil intent;* They discuss how to hide their traps. They say: “Who will see them?”  6 They search out new ways of wrongdoing; They secretly devise their shrewd strategy; The thinking within each one’s heart is unfathomable.  7 But God will shoot at them; Suddenly they will be wounded by an arrow.  8 Their own tongue will cause their downfall; All those looking on will shake their head.  9 Then all men will become afraid, And they will proclaim what God has done, And they will have insight into his deeds. 10 The righteous one will rejoice in Jehovah and take refuge in him; All the upright in heart will exult.*

To the director. A melody of David. A song. 65 Praise awaits you, O God, in Zion; We will pay our vows to you.  2 O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.  3 My errors have overwhelmed me, But you cover over our transgressions.  4 Happy is the one whom you choose and bring near To reside in your courtyards. We will be satisfied with the goodness of your house, Your holy temple.*  5 You will answer us with awe-inspiring deeds of righteousness, O God of our salvation; You are the Confidence of all the ends of the earth And of those distant across the sea.  6 You* firmly established the mountains by your power; You* are clothed with mightiness.  7 You* calm the raging seas, The crash of their waves and the turmoil of the nations.  8 The inhabitants of remote places will be awestruck by your signs; You will cause those from the sunrise to the sunset to shout joyfully.  9 You care for the earth, Making it abundantly fruitful* and very rich. The stream from God is full of water; You provide grain for them, For that is how you prepared the earth. 10 You drench its furrows and level off its plowed soil;* You soften it with showers of rain; you bless its growth. 11 You crown the year with your goodness; Your tracks overflow with abundance.* 12 The pastures of the wilderness keep overflowing,* And the hills are clothed with joyfulness. 13 The pastures are covered with flocks, And the valleys* are carpeted with grain. They shout in triumph, yes, they sing.

To the director. A song. A melody. 66 Shout in triumph to God, all the earth.  2 Sing praises* to his glorious name. Make his praise glorious.  3 Say to God: “How awe-inspiring your works are! Because of your great power, Your enemies will cringe before you.  4 All the earth will bow down to you; They will sing praises to you; They will sing praises to your name.” (Selah)  5 Come and see the works of God. His deeds toward the sons of men are awe-inspiring.  6 He changed the sea into dry land; They crossed the river on foot. There we rejoiced in him.  7 He rules forever by his might. His eyes keep watch on the nations. Those who are stubborn should not exalt themselves. (Selah)  8 Praise our God, you peoples, And let the sound of his praise be heard.  9 He preserves us alive;* He does not allow our feet to stumble.* 10 For you have examined us, O God; As silver is refined, so you have refined us. 11 You brought us into a hunting net; You put a crushing burden upon us.* 12 You allowed mortal man to ride over us;* We came through fire and through water; Then you brought us to a place of relief. 13 I will come into your house with whole burnt offerings; I will pay my vows to you 14 That my lips promised And my mouth spoke when I was in distress. 15 I will offer burnt offerings of fattened animals to you With the smoke of sacrificial rams. I will offer bulls along with male goats. (Selah) 16 Come and listen, all you who fear God, And I will tell you what he has done for me.* 17 I called to him with my mouth And glorified him with my tongue. 18 If I had harbored anything hurtful in my heart, Jehovah would not have heard me. 19 But God did hear; He paid attention to my prayer. 20 Praise to God, who did not reject my prayer Or withhold his loyal love from me.

To the director; to be accompanied with stringed instruments. A melody. A song. 67 God will show us favor and bless us; He will make his face shine upon us (Selah)  2 So that your way may be known throughout the earth, Your acts of salvation among all the nations.  3 Let peoples praise you, O God; Let all the peoples praise you.  4 Let nations rejoice and shout joyfully, For you will judge the peoples fairly. You will guide the nations of the earth. (Selah)  5 Let peoples praise you, O God; Let all the peoples praise you.  6 The earth will give its produce; God, our God, will bless us.  7 God will bless us, And all the ends of the earth will fear* him.

To the director. Of David. A melody. A song. 68 Let God rise up, let his enemies be scattered, And let those who hate him flee from before him.  2 As smoke is driven away, may you drive them away; As wax melts before the fire, So let the wicked perish before God.  3 But let the righteous rejoice; May they be overjoyed before God; May they exult with rejoicing.  4 Sing to God; sing praises* to his name. Sing to the One riding through the desert plains.* Jah* is his name! Rejoice before him!  5 A father of the fatherless and a protector* of widows Is God in his holy dwelling.  6 God gives those who are alone a home to dwell in; He leads prisoners out into prosperity. But the stubborn* must live in a parched land.  7 O God, when you led* your people, When you marched through the desert, (Selah)  8 The earth quaked; Heaven poured down rain* because of God; This Siʹnai quaked because of God, the God of Israel.  9 You made it rain in abundance, O God; You reinvigorated your exhausted people.* 10 They dwelled in your tent community; In your goodness, you provided for the poor, O God. 11 Jehovah gives the command; The women proclaiming the good news are a large army. 12 The kings of armies flee, they flee! She who remains at home shares in the spoil. 13 Although you men were lying among the campfires,* There will be the wings of a dove covered with silver, With pinions of fine* gold. 14 When the Almighty One scattered its kings, Snow fell in Zalʹmon.* 15 The mountain of Baʹshan is a mountain of God;* The mountain of Baʹshan is a mountain of peaks. 16 Why do you look with envy, you mountains of peaks, Toward the mountain that God has chosen* as his dwelling? Indeed, Jehovah will reside there forever. 17 The war chariots of God are tens of thousands, thousands upon thousands. Jehovah has come from Siʹnai into the holy place. 18 You ascended on high; You carried away captives; You took gifts in the form of men, Yes, even stubborn ones, to reside among them, O Jah God. 19 May Jehovah be praised, who daily carries our load, The true God of our salvation. (Selah) 20 The true God is for us a God who saves; And Jehovah the Sovereign Lord provides escape from death. 21 Yes, God will smash the heads of his enemies, The hairy crown of the head of anyone who continues* in his guilt. 22 Jehovah has said: “I will bring them back from Baʹshan; I will bring them back from the depths of the sea, 23 So that your foot may be awash in blood And the tongue of your dogs may have its portion from the enemies.” 24 They see your processions, O God, The processions of my God, my King, into the holy place. 25 The singers walk in front, the musicians playing stringed instruments after them; In between are the young women playing tambourines. 26 In congregated throngs,* praise God; Praise Jehovah, you who are from the Source of Israel. 27 There Benjamin, the youngest, is subduing them, Also the princes of Judah with their noisy crowd, The princes of Zebʹu·lun, the princes of Naphʹta·li. 28 Your God has decreed that you will be strong. Show your strength, O God, you who have acted in our behalf. 29 Because of your temple at Jerusalem, Kings will bring gifts to you. 30 Rebuke the wild beasts of the reeds, The assembly of bulls and their calves, Until the peoples bow down bringing* pieces of silver. But he scatters the peoples who delight in war. 31 Bronze articles will be brought* out of Egypt; Cush will hasten to offer gifts to God. 32 O kingdoms of the earth, sing to God, Sing praises* to Jehovah, (Selah) 33 To the one who rides the ancient heaven of heavens. Look! He thunders with his voice, his mighty voice. 34 Acknowledge God’s strength. His majesty is over Israel, And his strength is in the skies.* 35 God is awe-inspiring from his* grand sanctuary. He is the God of Israel, Who gives strength and power to the people. Praise to God.

See Glossary.

Or possibly, “You have given.”

Or possibly, “in his holy place.”

Or “Low Plain.”

Lit., “stronghold.”

Or possibly, “fortified.”

Or “grows feeble.”

Lit., “days.”

Or “will dwell.”

Or “Assign.”

Or “make music.”

See Glossary.

Or “my soul waits.”

Or “secure height.”

Or possibly, “All of you, as if he were a leaning wall, a stone wall ready to collapse.”

Or “his dignity.”

Or “wait silently, O my soul.”

Or “My soul thirsts.”

Lit., “My flesh is.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “as with fat and fatness.”

Or “My soul clings.”

Or “destroy my soul; kill me.”

Or “foxes.”

Or “boast.”

Or “They encourage one another to do evil.”

Or “boast.”

Lit., “all flesh.”

Or “sanctuary.”

Lit., “He.”

Lit., “He.”

Lit., “He.”

Lit., “making it overflow.”

Or “its ridges.”

Lit., “drip with fatness.”

Lit., “dripping.”

Or “low plains.”

Or “Make music.”

Or “sets our soul in life.”

Or “stagger; totter.”

Lit., “on our hips.”

Lit., “our head.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “honor.”

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “on the clouds.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Lit., “judge.”

Or “rebellious.”

Lit., “went out before.”

Lit., “dripped.”

Lit., “inheritance.”

Or possibly, “the sheepfolds.”

Or “yellowish-green.”

Or “It was as if it snowed in Zalmon.”

Or “a majestic mountain.”

Or “desires.”

Or “walks about.”

Lit., “In assemblies.”

Or possibly, “stamping down on.”

Or possibly, “Ambassadors will come.”

Or “Make music.”

Lit., “clouds.”

Lit., “your.”

^ (Pss. 63:1-64:10) O God, you are my God, I keep looking for you. I do thirst* for you. I am* faint with longing for you In a dry and parched land, where there is no water.  2 So I have looked upon you in the holy place; I have seen your strength and your glory.  3 Because your loyal love is better than life, My own lips will glorify you.  4 Thus I will praise you all my life; In your name I will lift up my hands.  5 I am* satisfied with the best and choicest portion,* So my mouth will praise you with joy on my lips.  6 I remember you while upon my bed; I meditate on you during the watches of the night.  7 For you are my helper, And I shout joyfully in the shadow of your wings.  8 I cling* to you; Your right hand keeps fast hold on me.  9 But those who seek to destroy my life* Will descend into the depths of the earth. 10 They will be handed over to the power of the sword; They will become food for jackals.* 11 But the king will rejoice in God. Every person swearing by Him will exult,* For the mouth of those speaking lies will be silenced.

To the director. A melody of David. 64 Hear my voice, O God, as I plead. Safeguard my life from the dreadfulness of the enemy.  2 Shield me from the secret plots of wicked men, From the crowd of wrongdoers.  3 They sharpen their tongue just like a sword; They aim their cruel words like arrows,  4 To shoot at the innocent from their hiding places; They shoot at him suddenly, without fear.  5 They hold fast to their evil intent;* They discuss how to hide their traps. They say: “Who will see them?”  6 They search out new ways of wrongdoing; They secretly devise their shrewd strategy; The thinking within each one’s heart is unfathomable.  7 But God will shoot at them; Suddenly they will be wounded by an arrow.  8 Their own tongue will cause their downfall; All those looking on will shake their head.  9 Then all men will become afraid, And they will proclaim what God has done, And they will have insight into his deeds. 10 The righteous one will rejoice in Jehovah and take refuge in him; All the upright in heart will exult.*

Or “My soul thirsts.”

Lit., “My flesh is.”

Or “My soul is.”

Lit., “as with fat and fatness.”

Or “My soul clings.”

Or “destroy my soul; kill me.”

Or “foxes.”

Or “boast.”

Or “They encourage one another to do evil.”

Or “boast.”

^ ***sn song 104 Praise Jah With Me***

Song 104

Praise Jah With Me

([Psalm 146:2])

1. Praise Jah with me;

Loud let it ring!

He gives us life, breath, and ev’ry good thing.

Each day and night,

His name we bless.

His perfect love clothes His almightiness.

We sing his praise, and his name we confess.

2. Praise Jah with me.

He satisfies

And hears our prayers as our needs he supplies.

His mighty arm

Strengthens the weak;

His holy spirit sustains all the meek.

His name we praise; Of his power we speak.

3. Praise Jah with me.

Our God is just;

He brings all comfort, in him we can trust.

Wrongs he will right;

Hearts he will heal.

Rich Kingdom blessings all mankind will feel.

Come let us praise him with joy and with zeal!

(See also Ps. 94:18, 19;[145:21;][147:1;][150:2].)

^ (Ps. 146:2) I will praise Jehovah all my life. I will sing praises* to my God as long as I live.

Or “make music.”

^ (Ps. 94:18, 19) When I said: “My foot is slipping,” Your loyal love, O Jehovah, kept supporting me. 19 When anxieties* overwhelmed me,* You comforted and soothed me.*

Or “disquieting thoughts.”

Or “became many inside of me.”

Or “Your consolations soothed my soul.”

^ (Ps. 145:21) My mouth will declare the praise of Jehovah; Let every living thing* praise his holy name forever and ever.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ (Ps. 147:1) Praise Jah!* It is good to sing praises* to our God; How pleasant and fitting it is to praise him!

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

^ (Ps. 150:2) Praise him for his mighty works. Praise him for his exceeding greatness.

^ ***w99 9/15 p. 9 Why Keep Your Promises?***

Our dedication to God is undoubtedly the most important promise we can make. By taking this step, we demonstrate that we want to serve Jehovah forever. While God’s commandments are not burdensome, it may not always be easy to do his will, living as we do in this wicked system of things. (2 Timothy 3:12;[1 John 5:3]) But once we have ‘put our hand to the plow’ and have become dedicated servants of Jehovah and disciples of his Son, Jesus Christ, we should never look back at the things of the world that we have left behind.—[Luke 9:62].

When we pray to Jehovah, we may feel moved to promise him that we will fight to overcome a weakness, cultivate a Christian quality, or increase some aspect of our theocratic activity. What will help us follow through on these promises?—Compare Ecclesiastes 5:2-5.

Sincere promises stem from the heart as well as the mind. Therefore, let us back up our promises to Jehovah by opening our hearts to him in prayer, honestly expressing our fears, desires, and weaknesses. Praying about a promise will strengthen our resolve to keep it. We could look on our promises to God as debts. When debts are large, payment has to be made gradually. Likewise, many promises we make to Jehovah will take time to fulfill. But by regularly giving him what we can, we show that we mean what we say, and he will bless us accordingly.

We can demonstrate that we take our promises seriously by praying about them often, perhaps each day. This will show our heavenly Father that we are sincere. It will also serve as a regular reminder. David left us a fine example in this regard. In song, he beseeched Jehovah: “Do hear, O God, my entreating cry. Do pay attention to my prayer. . . . I will make melody to your name forever, that I may pay my vows day after day.”—[Psalm 61:1,][8].

^ (2 Tim. 3:12) In fact, all those desiring to live with godly devotion in association with Christ Jesus will also be persecuted.

^ (1 John 5:3) For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome,

^ (Luke 9:62) Jesus said to him: “No man who has put his hand to a plow and looks at the things behind is well-suited for the Kingdom of God.”

^ (Eccl. 5:2-5) Do not be quick with your mouth, nor let your heart speak rashly before the true God, for the true God is in the heavens but you are on the earth. That is why your words should be few. 3 For a dream comes from too many preoccupations,* and the chatter of the stupid one comes from too many words. 4 Whenever you make a vow to God, do not delay to pay it, for he finds no pleasure in the stupid ones. What you vow, pay. 5 Better for you not to vow than to vow and not pay.

Or “too many cares.”

^ (Ps. 61:1) Hear, O God, my cry for help. Do pay attention to my prayer.

^ (Ps. 61:8) Then I will sing praises* to your name forever As I pay my vows day after day.

Or “make music.”

^ ***w15 4/15 pp. 25-26 Always Trust in Jehovah!***

TRUST IS ESSENTIAL TO OUR RELATIONSHIP WITH GOD

6. Why might it be especially challenging to trust in Jehovah when we are under stress?

6 Can you bring a distressing problem to Jehovah in prayer and thereafter be at peace, knowing that you have done what you can about the situation and he will handle the rest? Yes, you can! (Read Psalm 62:8; 1 Peter 5:7.) Learning to do so is an important aspect of developing a relationship with Jehovah. Yet, trusting that Jehovah will provide what you need can be quite a challenge. Why? One reason may be that Jehovah does not always respond right away.—[Ps. 13:1, 2;][74:10;][89:46;][90:13;][Hab. 1:2].

7. Why does Jehovah not always answer our prayers immediately?

7 Why does Jehovah not give us an immediate response to our every request? Recall that he likens our relationship with him to that of children with a father. ([Ps. 103:13]) A child cannot rightly expect a parent to grant every request or to do so right away. Some of a child’s requests may be mere passing whims. Others must wait till the time is right. Still others may not be in the child’s best interests or in the best interests of others involved. Furthermore, to concede immediately to a child’s every request would change the relationship to one of master and slave, the child being the master. Similarly, Jehovah may in our best interests allow time to pass before his response to our prayers becomes evident. That is his prerogative as our wise Creator, loving Master, and heavenly Father. Fulfilling all our requests right away would distort the proper relationship between us and him.—Compare Isaiah 29:16;[45:9].

8. What does Jehovah promise with regard to our personal limitations?

8 Another factor is that Jehovah is fully aware of our limitations. ([Ps. 103:14]) Therefore, he does not expect us to endure in our own strength but offers us his fatherly help. Of course, at times, we might feel that we cannot go on anymore. But Jehovah assures us that he will never allow his servants to suffer beyond their limit of endurance. Yes, he will “make the way out.” (Read 1 Corinthians 10:13.) Therefore, we have good reason to trust that Jehovah’s assessment of what we can bear is right.

9. What should we do when relief does not immediately follow our prayers for help?

9 When relief does not immediately follow our prayers for help, let us wait on the One who knows just when to act in our behalf. Remember that he too is exercising patience, for he is ever eager to come to our rescue. “Jehovah is waiting patiently to show you favor, and he will rise up to show you mercy. For Jehovah is a God of justice. Happy are all those keeping in expectation of him.”—[Isa. 30:18].

^ par. 6 (Ps. 62:8) Trust in him at all times, O people. Pour out your hearts before him. God is a refuge for us. (Selah)

^ par. 6 (1 Pet. 5:7) while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

^ par. 6 (Ps. 13:1, 2) How long, O Jehovah, will you forget me? Forever? How long will you hide your face from me?  2 How long will I* have anxious concern, With grief in my heart each day? How long will my enemy triumph over me?

Or “my soul.”

^ par. 6 (Ps. 74:10) How long, O God, will the adversary keep taunting? Will the enemy treat your name with disrespect forever?

^ par. 6 (Ps. 89:46) How long, O Jehovah, will you hide yourself? Will it be forever? Will your rage continue to burn like a fire?

^ par. 6 (Ps. 90:13) Return, O Jehovah! How long will this last? Have pity on your servants.

^ par. 6 (Hab. 1:2) How long, O Jehovah, must I cry for help, but you do not hear? How long must I ask for help from violence, but you do not intervene?*

Or “save.”

^ par. 7 (Ps. 103:13) As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him.

^ par. 7 (Isa. 29:16) How you twist things!* Should the potter be regarded the same as the clay? Should what is made say about its maker: “He did not make me”? And does what is formed say about its former: “He shows no understanding”?

Or “How perverse of you!”

^ par. 7 (Isa. 45:9) Woe to the one who contends* with his Maker,* For he is just an earthenware fragment Among the other earthenware fragments lying on the ground! Should the clay say to the Potter:* “What are you making?” Or should your work say: “He has no hands”?*

Or “argues.”

Or “with the One who formed him.”

Or “the One who formed it.”

Or possibly, “Or should the clay say: ‘Your work has no handles’?”

^ par. 8 (Ps. 103:14) For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ par. 8 (1 Cor. 10:13) No temptation has come upon you except what is common to men. But God is faithful, and he will not let you be tempted beyond what you can bear, but along with the temptation he will also make the way out so that you may be able to endure it.

^ par. 9 (Isa. 30:18) But Jehovah is waiting patiently* to show you favor, And he will rise up to show you mercy. For Jehovah is a God of justice. Happy are all those keeping in expectation of* him.

Or “keeping in expectation.”

Or “eagerly waiting for.”

^ ***w15 4/15 pp. 22-23 How Real Is Your Relationship With Jehovah?***

13 Consider this: From his prehuman existence, Jesus observed firsthand Jehovah’s response to the prayers of His human servants. Then, during his earthly ministry, Jesus used prayer as his means of communicating his feelings to his Father in heaven. Would he have done so—even spending an entire night in prayer—had he thought that Jehovah was not really listening? ([Luke 6:12;][22:40-46]) Would he have taught his disciples to pray had he thought that prayer was nothing more than a psychological crutch? Clearly, Jesus knew that prayer is real communication with Jehovah. On one occasion, Jesus said: “Father, I thank you that you have heard me. True, I knew that you always hear me.” We too can have confidence that Jehovah is the “Hearer of prayer.”—John 11:41, 42;[Ps. 65:2].

14, 15. (a) How do we benefit from being specific in our prayers? (b) How did one sisterʼs prayers help her strengthen her bond with Jehovah?

14 When you are specific in your prayers, you become more keenly aware of Jehovah’s answers, even though they may be subtle. Answered prayers will make Jehovah more real to you. In addition, the more you express your innermost concerns to Jehovah, the closer he will draw to you.

^ par. 13 (Luke 6:12) On one of those days he went out to the mountain to pray, and he spent the whole night in prayer to God.

^ par. 13 (Luke 22:40-46) On arriving at the place, he said to them: “Carry on prayer so that you do not enter into temptation.” 41 And he withdrew from them about a stone’s throw away, and he bent his knees and began to pray, 42 saying: “Father, if you want to, remove this cup from me. Nevertheless, let, not my will, but yours take place.” 43 Then an angel from heaven appeared to him and strengthened him. 44 But he was in such agony that he kept praying more earnestly; and his sweat became as drops of blood falling to the ground. 45 When he rose from prayer and went to the disciples, he found them slumbering, exhausted from grief. 46 He said to them: “Why are you sleeping? Get up and keep praying, so that you do not enter into temptation.”

^ par. 13 (John 11:41, 42) So they took the stone away. Then Jesus raised his eyes heavenward and said: “Father, I thank you that you have heard me. 42 True, I knew that you always hear me; but I spoke on account of the crowd standing around, so that they may believe that you sent me.”

^ par. 13 (Ps. 65:2) O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ ***w10 4/15 p. 5 Young People—Strengthen Your Desire to Serve Jehovah***

How Prayer Deepens Your Love for Jehovah

10, 11. How does prayer help you to strengthen your desire to serve God?

10 The second way in which you can strengthen your desire to serve Jehovah wholeheartedly is by means of your prayers. At [Psalm 65:2], we read: “O Hearer of prayer, even to you people of all flesh will come.” Even during the time that Israel was God’s covenant people, foreigners who came to Jehovah’s temple could approach him in prayer. (1 Ki. 8:41, 42) God is not partial. Those who observe his commandments have the assurance that he will listen to them. ([Prov. 15:8]) Surely, “people of all flesh” include you young ones.

^ par. 10 (Ps. 65:2) O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ par. 10 (1 Ki. 8:41, 42) “Also concerning the foreigner who is not part of your people Israel and who comes from a distant land because of your name* 42 (for they will hear about your great name and your mighty hand and your outstretched arm), and he comes and prays toward this house,

Or “reputation.”

^ par. 10 (Prov. 15:8) The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable to Jehovah, But the prayer of the upright is a pleasure to Him.

^ ***it-2 p. 668 Prayer***

Those Whom God Hears. People “of all flesh” may come to the “Hearer of prayer,” Jehovah God. ([Ps 65:2;][Ac 15:17]) Even during the period that Israel was God’s “private property,” his covenant people, foreigners could approach Jehovah in prayer by recognizing Israel as God’s appointed instrument and the temple at Jerusalem as his chosen place for sacrifice. ([De 9:29;] 2Ch 6:32, 33; compare [Isa 19:22].) Later, by Christ’s death, the distinction between Jew and Gentile was forever removed. ([Eph 2:11-16]) At the home of the Italian Cornelius, Peter recognized that “God is not partial, but in every nation the man that fears him and works righteousness is acceptable to him.” ([Ac 10:34, 35]) The determining factor, then, is the heart of the individual and what his heart is moving him to do. ([Ps 119:145;][La 3:41]) Those who observe God’s commandments and do “the things that are pleasing in his eyes” have the assurance that his “ears” are also open to them.—[1Jo 3:22;][Ps 10:17;][Pr 15:8;][1Pe 3:12].

^ (Ps. 65:2) O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ (Acts 15:17) so that the men who remain may earnestly seek Jehovah,* together with people of all the nations, people who are called by my name, says Jehovah,* who is doing these things,

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (Deut. 9:29) For they are your people and your personal possession,* whom you brought out with your great power and your outstretched arm.’

Or “your inheritance.”

^ (2 Chron. 6:32, 33) “Also concerning the foreigner who is not part of your people Israel and who comes from a distant land because of your great name* and your mighty hand and your outstretched arm, and he comes and prays toward this house, 33 may you then listen from the heavens, your dwelling place, and do all that the foreigner asks of you, so that all the peoples of the earth may know your name and fear you, as your people Israel do, and may know that your name has been called on this house that I have built.

Or “reputation.”

^ (Isa. 19:22) Jehovah will strike Egypt, striking and healing it; and they will return to Jehovah, and he will respond to their entreaties and heal them.

^ (Eph. 2:11-16) Therefore, remember that at one time you, people of the nations by fleshly descent, were the ones called “uncircumcision” by those called “circumcision,” which is made in the flesh by human hands. 12 At that time you were without Christ, alienated from the state of Israel, strangers to the covenants of the promise; you had no hope and were without God in the world. 13 But now in union with Christ Jesus, you who were once far off have come to be near by the blood of the Christ. 14 For he is our peace, the one who made the two groups one and destroyed the wall in between that fenced them off. 15 By means of his flesh he abolished the enmity, the Law of commandments consisting in decrees, in order to make the two groups in union with himself into one new man and to make peace, 16 and to reconcile fully both peoples in one body to God through the torture stake,* because he had killed off the enmity by means of himself.

See Glossary.

^ (Acts 10:34, 35) At this Peter began to speak, and he said: “Now I truly understand that God is not partial, 35 but in every nation the man who fears him and does what is right is acceptable to him.

^ (Ps. 119:145) I call with my whole heart. Answer me, O Jehovah. Your regulations I will observe.

^ (Lam. 3:41) Let us lift up our hearts along with our hands to God in the heavens:

^ (1 John 3:22) and whatever we ask we receive from him, because we are observing his commandments and doing what is pleasing in his eyes.

^ (Ps. 10:17) But you will hear the request of the meek, O Jehovah. You will make their hearts firm and pay close attention to them.

^ (Prov. 15:8) The sacrifice of the wicked is detestable to Jehovah, But the prayer of the upright is a pleasure to Him.

^ (1 Pet. 3:12) For the eyes of Jehovah* are on the righteous, and his ears listen to their supplication, but the face of Jehovah* is against those doing bad things.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ ***w06 6/1 p. 11 par. 7 Highlights From Book Two of Psalms***

63:3. God’s “loving-kindness is better than life” because without it, life is meaningless and purposeless. We are wise to cultivate friendship with Jehovah.

^ par. 7 (Ps. 63:3) Because your loyal love is better than life, My own lips will glorify you.

^ ***w06 6/1 p. 10 par. 5 Highlights From Book Two of Psalms***

68:18—Who were the “gifts in the form of men”? These were men from among those taken captive during the conquest of the Promised Land. Such men were later assigned to assist the Levites in their work.—[Ezra 8:20].

^ par. 5 (Ps. 68:18) You ascended on high; You carried away captives; You took gifts in the form of men, Yes, even stubborn ones, to reside among them, O Jah God.

^ par. 5 (Ezra 8:20) And there were 220 of the temple servants,* whom David and the princes gave to the service of the Levites, all of whom had been designated by name.

Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ ***sn song 81 “Give Us More Faith”***

Song 81

“Give Us More Faith”

([Luke 17:5])

1. Because we are imperfect, O Jehovah,

The inclination of our heart is flawed.

There is a sin that easily ensnares us—

A lack of faith in you, the living God.

(CHORUS)

Give us more faith, we beg of you, Jehovah.

Please help us out according to our need.

Give us more faith, according to your mercy,

That we may honor you in word and deed.

2. Apart from faith, no one can fully please you.

We must believe our faith will be repaid.

And as a shield, our faith provides a refuge.

We face the future firm and unafraid.

(CHORUS)

Give us more faith, we beg of you, Jehovah.

Please help us out according to our need.

Give us more faith, according to your mercy,

That we may honor you in word and deed.

(See also [Gen. 8:21;][Heb. 11:6;][12:1].)

^ (Luke 17:5) Now the apostles said to the Lord: “Give us more faith.”

^ (Gen. 8:21) And Jehovah began to smell a pleasing* aroma. So Jehovah said in his heart: “Never again will I curse* the ground on man’s account, for the inclination of the heart of man is bad from his youth up; and never again will I strike down every living thing as I have done.

Or “appeasing; soothing.” Lit., “restful.”

Or “call down evil upon.”

^ (Heb. 11:6) Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please God well, for whoever approaches God must believe that he is* and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.

Or “exists.”

^ (Heb. 12:1) So, then, because we have such a great cloud of witnesses surrounding us, let us also throw off every weight and the sin that easily entangles us, and let us run with endurance the race that is set before us,

^ ***ia pp. 162-166 He Protected, He Provided, He Persevered***

1, 2. (a) What changes did Joseph and his family face? (b) What bad news did Joseph have to tell his wife?

JOSEPH swung another load onto the donkey’s back. Picture him looking around at the darkened village of Bethlehem and patting the flank of the sturdy beast of burden. He was surely thinking of the long trip ahead. Egypt! A foreign people, a foreign tongue, foreign customs—how would his little family adapt to so much change?

2 It was not easy to tell the bad news to his beloved wife, Mary, but Joseph braced himself and did it. He told her of the dream in which an angel delivered this message from God: The king, Herod, wanted their little son dead! They had to leave right away. (Read Matthew 2:13, 14.) Mary was deeply concerned. How could anyone want to kill her innocent, harmless child? Neither Mary nor Joseph could fathom it. But they trusted in Jehovah, so they readied themselves.

3. Describe the departure of Joseph and his family from Bethlehem. (See also the picture.)

3 Unaware of the unfolding drama, Bethlehem slept as Joseph, Mary, and Jesus slipped out of the village in the darkness. Heading southward, with the sky beginning to lighten in the east, Joseph likely wondered what lay ahead. How could a lowly carpenter protect his family against forces so powerful? Would he always be able to provide for his own? Would he manage to persevere in carrying out this heavy assignment that Jehovah God had given him, to care for and raise this unique child? Joseph faced daunting challenges. As we consider how he rose to meet each one, we will see why fathers today—and all of us—need to imitate the faith of Joseph.

Joseph Protected His Family

4, 5. (a) How did Joseph’s life change forever? (b) How did an angel encourage Joseph to take on a weighty assignment?

4 Months earlier, in his hometown of Nazareth, Joseph found that his life changed forever after his engagement to the daughter of Heli. Joseph knew Mary as an innocent, faithful young woman. But then he learned that she was pregnant! He intended to divorce her secretly to protect her from scandal.* However, an angel spoke to him in a dream, explaining that Mary was pregnant by means of Jehovah’s holy spirit. The angel added that the son she bore would “save his people from their sins.” He further reassured Joseph: “Do not be afraid to take Mary your wife home.”—Matt. 1:18-21.

5 Joseph, a righteous and obedient man, did just that. He took on the weightiest of assignments: raising and caring for a son who was not his own but who was most precious to God. Later, in obedience to an imperial decree, Joseph and his pregnant wife went to Bethlehem to register. It was there that the child was born.

6-8. (a) What events led to another change in the lives of Joseph and his little family? (b) What evidence suggests that Satan sent the “star”? (See also footnote.)

6 Joseph did not take the family back to Nazareth. Instead, they settled in Bethlehem, just a few miles (about 10 km) from Jerusalem. They were poor, but Joseph did all he could to protect Mary and Jesus from want or suffering. In a short time, they took up living in a humble home. Then, when Jesus was no longer a baby but a small child—perhaps over a year old—their lives suddenly changed again.

7 A group of men arrived, astrologers from the East, likely from faraway Babylon. They had followed a “star” to the home of Joseph and Mary and were looking for a child who was to become king of the Jews. The men were deeply respectful.

8 Whether they knew it or not, the astrologers had put little Jesus in great peril. The “star” they had seen led them first, not to Bethlehem, but to Jerusalem.* There they told wicked King Herod that they were looking for a child who was to become king of the Jews. Their report filled the man with jealous rage.

9-11. (a) In what ways were forces greater than Herod or Satan at work? (b) How did the journey to Egypt differ from what is described in apocryphal myths?

9 Happily, though, there were forces greater than Herod or Satan at work. How so? Well, when the visitors reached Jesus’ house and saw him with his mother, they brought out gifts, asking for nothing in return. How strange it must have been for Joseph and Mary to find themselves suddenly in possession of “gold and frankincense and myrrh”—valuable commodities! The astrologers intended to go back and tell King Herod just where they had found the child. However, Jehovah intervened. By means of a dream, he instructed the astrologers to return home by another route.—Read Matthew 2:1-12.

10 Shortly after the astrologers left, Joseph received this warning from Jehovah’s angel: “Get up, take the young child and its mother and flee into Egypt, and stay there until I give you word; for Herod is about to search for the young child to destroy it.” ([Matt. 2:13]) So, as we noted at the outset, Joseph obeyed swiftly. He put his child’s safety above all else and took his family to Egypt. Because those pagan astrologers had brought such costly gifts, Joseph now had assets that might help the family during their sojourn ahead.

11 Apocryphal myths and legends later romanticized the journey to Egypt, claiming that little Jesus miraculously shortened the trip, rendered bandits harmless, and even made date palms bend down to his mother to yield their fruit.* In truth, it was simply a long, arduous trek into the unknown.

Joseph sacrificed his own comfort for the sake of his family

12. Parents who are raising children in this perilous world can learn what from Joseph?

12 Parents can learn a lot from Joseph. He readily set aside his work and sacrificed his own comfort in order to protect his family from danger. Clearly, he viewed his family as a sacred trust from Jehovah. Parents today raise their children in a perilous world, a world full of forces that would endanger, corrupt, or even destroy young ones. How admirable it is when mothers and fathers act decisively, as Joseph did, working hard to protect their children from such influences!

Joseph Provided for His Family

13, 14. How did Joseph and Mary end up raising their family in Nazareth?

13 It seems that the family did not stay long in Egypt, for soon the angel informed Joseph that Herod was dead. Joseph brought his family back to their homeland. An ancient prophecy had foretold that Jehovah would call his Son “out of Egypt.” ([Matt. 2:15]) Joseph helped to fulfill that prophecy, but where would he lead his family now?

14 Joseph was cautious. He wisely feared Herod’s successor, Archelaus, who was likewise vicious and murderous. Divine guidance led Joseph to take his family up north, away from Jerusalem and all its intrigues, back to his hometown of Nazareth in Galilee. There he and Mary raised their family.—Read Matthew 2:19-23.

15, 16. What was Joseph’s work like, and what tools might he have used?

15 They led a simple life—but not an easy one. The Bible refers to Joseph as the carpenter, using a word that embraces many ways of working with wood, such as cutting down timber, hauling it, and seasoning it for use in building houses, boats, small bridges, carts, wheels, yokes, and all kinds of farm implements. ([Matt. 13:55]) It was hard physical work. A carpenter in Bible times often worked near the doorway of his modest house or in a shop adjacent to it.

16 Joseph used a wide range of tools, some likely handed down from his father. He may have used a square, a plummet, a chalk line, a hatchet, a saw, an adze, a hammer, a mallet, chisels, a drill that he worked by pulling a bow back and forth, various glues, and perhaps some nails, though they were costly.

^ par. 2 (Matt. 2:13, 14) After they had departed, look! Jehovah’s* angel appeared to Joseph in a dream, saying: “Get up, take the young child and his mother and flee to Egypt, and stay there until I give you word, for Herod is about to search for the young child to kill him.” 14 So Joseph got up and by night took along the young child and the child’s mother and went into Egypt.

See App. A5.

^ par. 4 (Matt. 1:18-21) But this is how the birth of Jesus Christ took place. During the time his mother Mary was promised in marriage to Joseph, she was found to be pregnant by holy spirit* before they were united. 19 However, because her husband Joseph was righteous and did not want to make her a public spectacle, he intended to divorce her secretly. 20 But after he had thought these things over, look! Jehovah’s* angel appeared to him in a dream, saying: “Joseph, son of David, do not be afraid to take your wife Mary home, for what has been conceived* in her is by holy spirit. 21 She will give birth to a son, and you are to name him Jesus,* for he will save his people from their sins.”

Or “active force.”

This is the first of 237 places in the Christian Greek Scriptures where the divine name, Jehovah, occurs in the main text of this version. See App. A5.

Or “begotten.”

Corresponds to the Hebrew name Jeshua, or Joshua, which means “Jehovah Is Salvation.”

^ par. 9 (Matt. 2:1-12) After Jesus had been born in Bethʹle·hem of Ju·deʹa in the days of Herod* the king, look! astrologers* from the East came to Jerusalem, 2 saying: “Where is the one born king of the Jews? For we saw his star when we were in the East, and we have come to do obeisance* to him.” 3 At hearing this, King Herod was agitated, and all Jerusalem with him. 4 On gathering together all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he inquired of them where the Christ* was to be born. 5 They said to him: “In Bethʹle·hem of Ju·deʹa, for this is how it has been written through the prophet: 6 ‘And you, O Bethʹle·hem of the land of Judah, are by no means the most insignificant city among the governors of Judah, for out of you will come a governing one, who will shepherd my people Israel.’” 7 Then Herod secretly summoned the astrologers and carefully ascertained from them the time of the star’s appearing. 8 When sending them to Bethʹle·hem, he said: “Go make a careful search for the young child, and when you have found him, report back to me so that I too may go and do obeisance to him.” 9 After they had heard the king, they went their way, and look! the star they had seen when they were in the East went ahead of them until it came to a stop above where the young child was. 10 On seeing the star, they rejoiced with great joy. 11 And when they went into the house, they saw the young child with Mary his mother, and falling down, they did obeisance* to him. They also opened their treasures and presented him with gifts—gold and frankincense and myrrh. 12 However, because they were given divine warning in a dream not to return to Herod, they departed for their country by another way.

See Glossary.

Or “magi.”

Or “to bow down.”

Or “the Messiah; the Anointed One.”

Or “bowed down.”

^ par. 10 (Matt. 2:13) After they had departed, look! Jehovah’s* angel appeared to Joseph in a dream, saying: “Get up, take the young child and his mother and flee to Egypt, and stay there until I give you word, for Herod is about to search for the young child to kill him.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 13 (Matt. 2:15) He stayed there until the death of Herod. This fulfilled what was spoken by Jehovah* through his prophet, saying: “Out of Egypt I called my son.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 14 (Matt. 2:19-23) When Herod had died, look! Jehovah’s* angel appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt 20 and said: “Get up, take the young child and his mother and go into the land of Israel, for those who were seeking the life* of the young child are dead.” 21 So he got up and took the young child and the child’s mother and entered into the land of Israel. 22 But hearing that Ar·che·laʹus ruled Ju·deʹa instead of his father Herod, he was afraid to go there. Moreover, being given divine warning in a dream, he withdrew into the territory of Galʹi·lee. 23 And he came and settled in a city named Nazʹa·reth, in order to fulfill what was spoken through the prophets: “He will be called a Naz·a·reneʹ.”*

See App. A5.

Or “soul.”

Probably from the Hebrew expression “sprout.”

^ par. 15 (Matt. 13:55) Is this not the carpenter’s son? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brothers James and Joseph and Simon and Judas?

^ par. 4 In those days, engagement was viewed in almost the same light as marriage.

^ par. 8 This “star” was no natural astronomical phenomenon; nor was it sent by God. Clearly, Satan used that supernatural manifestation as part of his wicked design to destroy Jesus.

^ par. 11 The Bible clearly shows that Jesus’ first miracle, “the beginning of his signs,” did not occur until after his baptism.—[John 2:1-11].

^ (John 2:1-11) And on the third day a marriage feast took place in Caʹna of Galʹi·lee, and the mother of Jesus was there. 2 Jesus and his disciples were also invited to the marriage feast. 3 When the wine ran short, the mother of Jesus said to him: “They have no wine.” 4 But Jesus said to her: “Woman, why is that of concern to me and to you?* My hour has not yet come.” 5 His mother said to those serving: “Do whatever he tells you.” 6 Now there were six stone water jars sitting there as required by the purification rules of the Jews, each able to hold two or three liquid measures.* 7 Jesus said to them: “Fill the jars with water.” So they filled them to the brim. 8 Then he said to them: “Now draw some out and take it to the director of the feast.” So they took it. 9 When the director of the feast tasted the water that had now been turned into wine, not knowing where it came from (although the servants who had drawn out the water knew), the director of the feast called the bridegroom 10 and said to him: “Everyone else puts out the fine wine first, and when people are intoxicated, the inferior. You have saved the fine wine until now.” 11 Jesus did this in Caʹna of Galʹi·lee as the beginning of his signs, and he made his glory manifest, and his disciples put their faith in him.

Lit., “What to me and to you, woman?” This is an idiom indicating objection. The use of “woman” does not denote disrespect.

Likely the liquid measure was the bath that equaled 22 L (5.81 gal). See App. B14.

^ ***sn song 88 Children Are a Trust From God***

Song 88

Children Are a Trust From God

(Psalm 127:3-5)

1. When a man becomes a father

And a woman has a child of her own,

They share a trust, they must remember,

That is not theirs, not theirs alone.

The gift they share is from Jehovah;

Of life and love he is the one true Source.

To parents he gives sure direction

That they may follow the wisest course.

(CHORUS)

A sacred trust you have been given;

A precious life is in your hands.

You can bestow the greatest favor;

Instruct your child in God’s commands.

2. All the words God has commanded—

They must always prove to be on your heart.

These words you’ll speak to sons and daughters;

This is your trust, this is your part.

To them you’ll speak along your roadway,

When you rise up and when you are at rest.

In years to come, may they remember,

May they be faithful, may they be blessed.

(CHORUS)

A sacred trust you have been given;

A precious life is in your hands.

You can bestow the greatest favor;

Instruct your child in God’s commands.

(See also Deut. 6:6, 7;[Eph. 6:4;][1 Tim. 4:16].)

^ (Ps. 127:3-5) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

Or “Children.”

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ (Eph. 6:4) And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

^ (Pss. 69:0-73:28) To the director; set to “The Lilies.” Of David. 69 Save me, O God, for the waters threaten my life.*  2 I have sunk down into the deep mud, where there is no solid ground. I have come into deep waters, And the rushing stream has swept me away.  3 I am exhausted from calling out; My throat has become hoarse. My eyes have grown weary while waiting for my God.  4 Those hating me without cause Are more numerous than the hairs of my head. Those who would do away with me, My treacherous enemies,* have become many. I was forced to hand over what I had not stolen.  5 O God, you are aware of my foolishness, And my guilt is not hidden from you.  6 May those hoping in you not be put to shame because of me, O Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies. May those seeking you not be humiliated because of me, O God of Israel.  7 I suffer reproach on your account; Humiliation covers my face.  8 I have become a stranger to my brothers, A foreigner to the sons of my mother.  9 Zeal for your house has consumed me, And the reproaches of those reproaching you have fallen upon me. 10 When I humbled myself* with fasting,* I was reproached for it. 11 When I made sackcloth my clothing, I became an object of scorn* to them. 12 I am the talk of those sitting in the city gate, And the drunkards make me the subject of their songs. 13 But may my prayer come to you, O Jehovah, at an acceptable time. In your abundant loyal love, O God, Answer me with your sure acts of salvation. 14 Rescue me from the mire; Do not let me sink down. Rescue me from those who hate me And from the deep waters. 15 Do not let the rushing floodwaters sweep me away, Or let the deep swallow me, Or let the well* close its mouth over me. 16 Answer me, O Jehovah, for your loyal love is good. According to your abundant mercy turn toward me, 17 And do not hide your face from your servant. Answer me quickly, for I am in distress. 18 Come near to me and rescue me;* Redeem me on account of my enemies. 19 You know my reproach and my disgrace and my humiliation. You see all my foes. 20 Reproach has broken my heart, and the wound is incurable.* I was hoping for sympathy, but there was none, And for comforters, but I found none. 21 But for food they gave me poison,* And for my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink. 22 Let their table become a trap for them, And their prosperity, a snare. 23 Let their eyes become darkened so that they cannot see, And make their hips tremble constantly. 24 Pour out upon them your indignation,* And may your burning anger overtake them. 25 Let their encampment* become desolate; Let there be no inhabitant in their tents. 26 For they pursue the one whom you struck, And they keep recounting the pains of those you wounded. 27 Add more guilt to their guilt, And may they have no share in your righteousness. 28 Let them be erased from the book of the living,* And may they not be enrolled among the righteous. 29 But I am afflicted and in pain. May your saving power, O God, protect me. 30 I will sing praises to the name of God, And I will magnify him with thanksgiving. 31 This will please Jehovah more than a bull, More than a young bull with horns and hooves. 32 The meek will see it and rejoice. You who are seeking God, may your hearts revive. 33 For Jehovah is listening to the poor, And he will not despise his captive people. 34 Let heaven and earth praise him, The seas and everything that moves in them. 35 For God will save Zion And will rebuild the cities of Judah, And they will dwell there and possess it.* 36 The descendants of his servants will inherit it, And those who love his name will reside in it.

To the director. Of David, to serve as a reminder.* 70 O God, save me; O Jehovah, hurry to help me.  2 May those seeking to take my life* Be put to shame and disgraced. May those who delight in my calamity Retreat in humiliation.  3 May those who are saying: “Aha! Aha!” Be driven back in shame.  4 But let those who are seeking you Exult and rejoice in you. May those who love your acts of salvation always say: “May God be magnified!”  5 But I am helpless and poor; O God, act quickly in my behalf. You are my helper and my rescuer; O Jehovah, do not delay.

71 In you, O Jehovah, I have taken refuge. May I never be put to shame.  2 In your righteousness save me and rescue me. Incline your ear* to me and save me.  3 Become for me a rock fortress Where I can always enter. Give the command to save me, For you are my crag and my stronghold.  4 O my God, rescue me from the hand of the wicked, From the grasp of the unjust oppressor.  5 For you are my hope, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah; I have trusted in you* since my youth.  6 I have depended on you from birth; It was you who took me from my mother’s womb. I praise you constantly.  7 I have become like a miracle to many, But you are my strong refuge.  8 My mouth is filled with your praise; All day long I tell about your splendor.  9 Do not cast me off in my old age; Do not abandon me when my strength fails. 10 My enemies speak against me, And those seeking to take my life* conspire together, 11 Saying: “God has abandoned him. Chase after him and seize him, for there is no one to save him.” 12 O God, do not remain far away from me. O my God, hurry to help me. 13 May those who are resisting me* Be put to shame and perish. May those seeking my calamity Be covered with disgrace and humiliation. 14 But as for me, I will continue to wait; I will add to your praise. 15 My mouth will recount your righteousness, All day long your acts of salvation, Though they are too many for me to grasp.* 16 I will come and tell about your mighty acts, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah; I will mention your righteousness, yours alone. 17 O God, you have taught me from my youth, And until now I keep declaring your wonderful works. 18 Even when I am old and gray, O God, do not abandon me. Let me tell the next generation about your power* And about your mightiness to all those who are to come. 19 Your righteousness, O God, reaches to the heights; You have done great things; O God, who is like you? 20 Though you have made me experience much distress and calamity, Revive me again; Bring me up from the depths* of the earth. 21 May you increase my greatness And surround and comfort me. 22 Then I will praise you on a stringed instrument Because of your faithfulness, O my God. I will sing your praises* with the harp, O Holy One of Israel. 23 My lips will shout joyfully as I sing praises to you, For you have saved my life.* 24 My tongue will speak about* your righteousness all day long, For those seeking my destruction will be ashamed and disgraced.

Regarding Solomon. 72 O God, give your judgments to the king, And endow the son of the king with your righteousness.  2 May he plead the cause of your people with righteousness, And of your lowly ones with justice.  3 May the mountains bring peace to the people, And may the hills bring righteousness.  4 Let him defend* the lowly among the people, Let him save the sons of the poor, And let him crush the defrauder.  5 They will fear you as long as there is a sun And as long as the moon remains, For generation after generation.  6 He will be like the rain that falls on the mown grass, Like showers of rain that water the earth.  7 In his days the righteous will flourish,* And peace will abound until the moon is no more.  8 He will have subjects* from sea to sea And from the River* to the ends of the earth.  9 The desert dwellers will bow down before him, And his enemies will lick the dust. 10 The kings of Tarʹshish and of the islands will pay tribute. The kings of Sheʹba and of Seʹba will present gifts. 11 All the kings will bow down before him, And all the nations will serve him. 12 For he will rescue the poor who cry for help, Also the lowly one and whoever has no helper. 13 He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save. 14 From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes. 15 May he live and be given the gold of Sheʹba. May prayers be said for him continually, And may he be blessed all day long. 16 There will be an abundance of grain on the earth; On the top of the mountains it will overflow. His fruit will flourish as in Lebʹa·non, And in the cities people will blossom like the vegetation of the earth. 17 May his name endure forever, And may it prosper as long as the sun. May people obtain a blessing for themselves by means of him; May all nations pronounce him happy. 18 May Jehovah God be praised, Israel’s God, Who alone does wonderful things. 19 May his glorious name be praised forever, And may his glory fill the whole earth. Amen and Amen. 20 This completes the prayers of David, the son of Jesʹse.

A melody of Aʹsaph. 73 God is truly good to Israel, to those pure in heart.  2 As for me, my feet had almost strayed; My steps had nearly slipped.  3 For I became envious of the arrogant* When I would see the peace of the wicked.  4 For they have no pain in their death; Their bodies are healthy.*  5 They are not troubled like other humans, Nor do they suffer like other men.  6 Therefore, haughtiness is their necklace; Violence clothes them as a garment.  7 Their prosperity* makes their eyes bulge; They have exceeded the imaginations of the heart.  8 They scoff and say evil things. They arrogantly threaten oppression.  9 They speak as if they were as high as heaven, And their tongues swagger about in the earth. 10 So his people turn aside to them, And they drink from their abundant water. 11 They say: “How does God know? Does the Most High really have knowledge?” 12 Yes, these are the wicked, who always have it easy. They keep increasing their wealth. 13 Surely in vain I have kept my heart pure And washed my hands in innocence. 14 And I was troubled all day long; Every morning I was chastised. 15 But if I had said these things, I would have betrayed your people.* 16 When I tried to understand it, It was troubling to me 17 Until I entered the grand sanctuary of God, And I discerned their future. 18 Surely you place them on slippery ground. You make them fall to their ruin. 19 How suddenly they are devastated! How sudden is their finish as they come to a terrible end! 20 Like a dream when one wakes up, O Jehovah, When you rouse yourself, you will dismiss* their image. 21 But my heart was sour, And deep inside* I felt sharp pain. 22 I was unreasoning and lacked understanding; I was like a senseless beast before you. 23 But now I am continually with you; You have taken hold of my right hand. 24 You guide me with your advice, And afterward you will lead me to glory. 25 Whom do I have in the heavens? And besides you I desire nothing on earth. 26 My body and my heart may fail, But God is the rock of my heart and my portion forever. 27 Truly, those keeping far from you will perish. You will put an end to* everyone who immorally* leaves you. 28 But as for me, drawing near to God is good for me. I have made the Sovereign Lord Jehovah my refuge, To declare all your works.

Or “have come to my soul.”

Or “enemies for no reason.”

Lit., “my soul.”

Or possibly, “When I wept and fasted.”

Lit., “a proverb.”

Or “pit.”

Or “Come near to my soul and reclaim it.”

Or “and I am to the point of despair.”

Or “a poisonous plant.”

Or “wrath.”

Or “walled camp.”

Or “book of life.”

That is, the land.

Or “to bring to remembrance.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or “You are my confidence.”

Or “seeking my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “number.”

Lit., “arm.”

Or “watery deeps.”

Or “make music to you.”

Or “redeemed my soul.”

Or “meditate on.”

Lit., “judge.”

Lit., “sprout.”

Or “will rule.”

That is, the Euphrates.

Or “souls.”

Or “redeem their souls.”

Or “boasters.”

Or “Their paunch is fat.”

Lit., “fat.”

Lit., “the generation of your sons.”

Lit., “despise.”

Lit., “in my kidneys.”

Lit., “silence.”

Or “unfaithfully.”

^ (Ps. 73:1-28) God is truly good to Israel, to those pure in heart.  2 As for me, my feet had almost strayed; My steps had nearly slipped.  3 For I became envious of the arrogant* When I would see the peace of the wicked.  4 For they have no pain in their death; Their bodies are healthy.*  5 They are not troubled like other humans, Nor do they suffer like other men.  6 Therefore, haughtiness is their necklace; Violence clothes them as a garment.  7 Their prosperity* makes their eyes bulge; They have exceeded the imaginations of the heart.  8 They scoff and say evil things. They arrogantly threaten oppression.  9 They speak as if they were as high as heaven, And their tongues swagger about in the earth. 10 So his people turn aside to them, And they drink from their abundant water. 11 They say: “How does God know? Does the Most High really have knowledge?” 12 Yes, these are the wicked, who always have it easy. They keep increasing their wealth. 13 Surely in vain I have kept my heart pure And washed my hands in innocence. 14 And I was troubled all day long; Every morning I was chastised. 15 But if I had said these things, I would have betrayed your people.* 16 When I tried to understand it, It was troubling to me 17 Until I entered the grand sanctuary of God, And I discerned their future. 18 Surely you place them on slippery ground. You make them fall to their ruin. 19 How suddenly they are devastated! How sudden is their finish as they come to a terrible end! 20 Like a dream when one wakes up, O Jehovah, When you rouse yourself, you will dismiss* their image. 21 But my heart was sour, And deep inside* I felt sharp pain. 22 I was unreasoning and lacked understanding; I was like a senseless beast before you. 23 But now I am continually with you; You have taken hold of my right hand. 24 You guide me with your advice, And afterward you will lead me to glory. 25 Whom do I have in the heavens? And besides you I desire nothing on earth. 26 My body and my heart may fail, But God is the rock of my heart and my portion forever. 27 Truly, those keeping far from you will perish. You will put an end to* everyone who immorally* leaves you. 28 But as for me, drawing near to God is good for me. I have made the Sovereign Lord Jehovah my refuge, To declare all your works.

Or “boasters.”

Or “Their paunch is fat.”

Lit., “fat.”

Lit., “the generation of your sons.”

Lit., “despise.”

Lit., “in my kidneys.”

Lit., “silence.”

Or “unfaithfully.”

^ ***sn song 92 “Preach the Word”***

Song 92

“Preach the Word”

(2 Timothy 4:2)

1. God has commanded us this day;

He has given us a charge to obey.

At all times, be ready to impart

The reason for the hope within your heart.

(CHORUS)

So preach the Word,

Oh, how vital that all hear!

Preach the Word,

As this system’s end draws near.

Preach the Word,

Help the meek to understand.

Preach the Word,

Throughout the land!

2. Seasons of trouble we will face;

Opposition may bring shame and disgrace.

Though preaching may out of season seem,

Our trust is in our God, who is supreme.

(CHORUS)

So preach the Word,

Oh, how vital that all hear!

Preach the Word,

As this system’s end draws near.

Preach the Word,

Help the meek to understand.

Preach the Word,

Throughout the land!

3. Seasons of favor we will see,

And the need for us to teach, there will be.

The way to salvation we proclaim

And help to sanctify Jehovah’s name.

(CHORUS)

So preach the Word,

Oh, how vital that all hear!

Preach the Word,

As this system’s end draws near.

Preach the Word,

Help the meek to understand.

Preach the Word,

Throughout the land!

(See also [Matt. 10:7;][24:14;][Acts 10:42;][1 Pet. 3:15].)

^ (2 Tim. 4:2) Preach the word; be at it urgently in favorable times and difficult times; reprove, reprimand, exhort, with all patience and art of teaching.

^ (Matt. 10:7) As you go, preach, saying: ‘The Kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.’

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Acts 10:42) Also, he ordered us to preach to the people and to give a thorough witness that this is the one decreed by God to be judge of the living and the dead.

^ (1 Pet. 3:15) But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts, always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.

^ ***w10 12/15 pp. 7-11 Be Zealous for True Worship***

2. What is the most urgent task for true Christians today?

2 For true Christians today, nothing is more urgent than preaching the good news of the Kingdom and making disciples of people of all the nations. ([Matt. 24:14;][28:19, 20]) Quoting Jesus, the disciple Mark wrote that this work must be done “first,” that is, before the end comes. ([Mark 13:10]) That, of course, is the way it should be. Jesus said: “The harvest is great, but the workers are few.” A harvest cannot wait; it must be brought in before the season is over.—[Matt. 9:37].

3. How have many responded to the urgent need to preach?

3 Because the preaching work is of such importance to us, it deserves our giving it as much of our time, energy, and attention as possible. Commendably, many are doing just that. Some have simplified their personal affairs so as to take up the full-time ministry as pioneers or missionaries or to serve at one of the Bethel homes around the world. Their life is very busy. They may have made many sacrifices, and they have many challenges to meet. Yet, they are richly blessed by Jehovah. We are happy for them. (Read Luke 18:28-30.) Others, while unable to join the ranks of full-time proclaimers, devote as much time as possible to this lifesaving work, which includes helping our children to get saved.—[Deut. 6:6, 7].

4. Why might some tend to lose the sense of urgency?

4 As we have seen, a sense of urgency is usually connected with a time limit, a deadline, an end. We are living in the time of the end, and there is plenty of evidence—both Scriptural and historical—to prove that. ([Matt. 24:3,][33;] 2 Tim. 3:1-5) Still, no man knows the exact time when the end will come. When giving the details of “the sign” marking “the conclusion of the system of things,” Jesus specifically said: “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.” ([Matt. 24:36]) That being so, some might find it difficult to maintain a sense of urgency year after year, especially if they have been doing so for a long time. ([Prov. 13:12]) Do you at times find yourself feeling that way? What can help us to develop or maintain a sense of urgency for the task that Jehovah God and Jesus Christ want us to do today?

Consider Our Exemplar, Jesus

5. In what ways did Jesus reflect a sense of urgency in connection with the ministry?

5 Of all those who demonstrated urgency in their service to God, Jesus Christ is surely the foremost example. One reason for his urgency was that he had much to do in a span of only three and a half years. Nevertheless, Jesus accomplished more with regard to true worship than anyone else has ever done. He made known his Father’s name and purpose, preached the good news of the Kingdom, exposed the hypocrisy and false teachings of the religious leaders, and upheld Jehovah’s sovereignty even to the point of death. He spared no effort in traversing the land—teaching, helping, and curing the people. ([Matt. 9:35]) No one has ever accomplished so much in such a short time. Jesus worked as hard as anyone possibly could.—[John 18:37].

6. What was the focus in Jesus’ life?

6 What moved Jesus to work tirelessly throughout his ministry? From Daniel’s prophecy, Jesus could have known where he was in relation to Jehovah’s timetable. ([Dan. 9:27]) Thus, as noted, his earthly ministry was to end “at the half of the week,” or after three and a half years. Shortly after his triumphant entry into Jerusalem in the spring of 33 C.E., Jesus said: “The hour has come for the Son of man to be glorified.” ([John 12:23]) Although Jesus knew that his death was imminent, he did not let that become the focus in his life, the prime reason for working hard. Rather, he focused on using every opportunity to do his Father’s will and to show love to his fellow humans. That love moved him to gather and train disciples, sending them out in preaching campaigns. That was so that they would carry on the work he had started and would accomplish even greater works than he did.—Read John 14:12.

7, 8. How did the disciples react to Jesus’ cleansing of the temple, and why did Jesus act that way?

7 One event in Jesus’ life forcefully demonstrated what zeal he had. It was early in his ministry, in the Passover season of 30 C.E. Jesus and his disciples came to Jerusalem and saw in the temple “those selling cattle and sheep and doves and the money brokers in their seats.” What was Jesus’ response, and what impression did it make on his disciples?—Read John 2:13-17.

8 What Jesus did and said on that occasion fittingly brought to the disciples’ mind the prophetic words of one psalm by David: “Sheer zeal for your house has eaten me up.” ([Ps. 69:9]) Why? Because what Jesus did involved a great deal of risk and danger. After all, the temple authorities—the priests, the scribes, and others—were behind the scandalous profit-making business taking place there. To expose and disrupt their scheme, Jesus was pitting himself against the religious establishment of the day. As the disciples correctly assessed the situation, ‘zeal for God’s house,’ or zeal for true worship, was clearly in evidence. What, though, is zeal? Is it different from urgency?

Urgency and Zeal Compared

9. How may zeal be described?

9 One dictionary defines “zeal” as “eagerness and ardent interest in pursuit of something,” and it offers as synonyms such words as passion, fervor, ardor, and enthusiasm. Surely Jesus’ ministry can be characterized by all these expressions. Hence, Today’s English Version renders the verse: “My devotion to your house, O God, burns in me like a fire.” Interestingly, in some Oriental languages, the term for “zeal” is made up of two parts that literally mean “hot heart,” as though the heart were burning. It is no wonder that the disciples recalled David’s words when they saw what Jesus did at the temple. What, though, set Jesus’ heart on fire, as it were, and propelled, or moved, him to act that way?

10. What is the meaning of “zeal” as used in the Bible?

10 The word “zeal” in David’s psalm is derived from a Hebrew word that is often translated “jealous” or “jealousy” in other parts of the Bible. The New World Translation sometimes renders it “exacting exclusive devotion.” (Read Exodus 20:5; 34:14; Joshua 24:19.) One Bible dictionary says of this term: “It is often used in connection with the marriage relation . . . Just as jealousy in husband or wife is the forceful assertion of an exclusive right, so God asserts His claim, and vindicates it, on those who are His sole possession.” Thus, zeal in the Biblical sense is more than fervor or enthusiasm for a certain pursuit, such as many fans show for their favorite sport. David’s zeal was jealousy in the positive sense, that is, an intolerance of rivalry or reproach, a strong urge to protect a good name or to correct an injury.

11. What was it that moved Jesus to exert himself zealously?

11 Jesus’ disciples were not mistaken in associating David’s words with what they saw Jesus do at the temple. Jesus exerted himself not simply because he had a deadline but because he was zealous—or jealous—for his Father’s name and for pure worship. When he saw the reproach and blasphemy heaped upon God’s name, he was rightly zealous, or jealous, and acted to correct the situation. When Jesus saw the humble people oppressed and exploited by the religious leaders, his zeal moved him to bring relief to the people as well as to utter forceful denunciations against the oppressive religious leaders.—[Matt. 9:36;][23:2,][4,][27, 28,][33].

Be Zealous for True Worship

12, 13. What have Christendom’s religious leaders today done regarding (a) God’s name? (b) God’s Kingdom?

12 The religious scene around us today is similar—if not worse—than it was in Jesus’ day. For example, recall that the first thing Jesus taught his followers to pray for concerned God’s name: “Let your name be sanctified.” ([Matt. 6:9]) Do we see the religious leaders, especially the clergy of Christendom, teaching people to know God by his name and to sanctify, or honor, that name? On the contrary, they have misrepresented God by such false teachings as the Trinity, immortality of the human soul, and hellfire, making God appear mysterious, unfathomable, cruel, even sadistic. They have also brought reproach on God by their scandals and their hypocrisy. (Read Romans 2:21-24.) Furthermore, they have done everything possible to hide God’s personal name, even removing it from their translations of the Bible. They thus hinder people from drawing close to God and cultivating a personal relationship with him.—[Jas. 4:7, 8].

13 Jesus also taught his followers to pray for God’s Kingdom: “Let your kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also upon earth.” ([Matt. 6:10]) Though Christendom’s religious leaders often repeat that prayer, they have urged people to support political and other human institutions. Moreover, they belittle those who endeavor to preach and bear witness to this Kingdom. As a result, among many who claim to be Christians, God’s Kingdom is no longer a topic for discussion, let alone a matter of faith.

14. How have the clergy of Christendom watered down God’s Word?

14 In prayer to God, Jesus clearly stated: “Your word is truth.” ([John 17:17]) And before leaving the earthly scene, Jesus indicated that he would appoint “the faithful and discreet slave” to provide spiritual food for his people. ([Matt. 24:45]) Though quick to claim stewardship of God’s Word, have the clergy of Christendom proved to be faithful to the Master’s trust? No. They have been inclined to label what the Bible says as fable or myth. Rather than feeding their flock with spiritual food, thus bringing them comfort and enlightenment, the clergy have tickled the believers’ ears with human philosophy. In addition, they have watered down God’s moral standards to cater to the so-called new morality.—2 Tim. 4:3, 4.

15. How do you feel about all that the clergy have done in the name of God?

15 Because of all that has been done—supposedly in the name of the God of the Bible—many sincere people have become disillusioned or have completely lost their faith in God and in the Bible. They have fallen prey to Satan and his wicked system of things. When you see and hear about such things taking place day after day, how do you feel? As a servant of Jehovah, when you see the reproach and blasphemy heaped upon God’s name, do you not feel impelled to do what you can to right the wrong? When you see sincere and honesthearted people being deceived and exploited, do you not feel moved to bring comfort to the oppressed souls? When Jesus saw people of his day being “skinned and thrown about like sheep without a shepherd,” he did not just feel pity. He “started to teach them many things.” ([Matt. 9:36;][Mark 6:34]) We have every reason to be zealous for true worship, as Jesus was.

16, 17. (a) What should impel us to exert ourselves in the ministry? (b) What will we consider in the following article?

16 When we view our ministry that way, the apostle Paul’s words found at 1 Timothy 2:3, 4 take on special meaning. (Read.) We work hard in the ministry not only because we know we are living in the last days but also because we realize that it is God’s will. He wants people to come to a knowledge of the truth so that they too can learn to worship and serve him and be blessed. We are impelled to exert ourselves in the ministry, not primarily because of a time limit, but because we want to honor God’s name and help people to come to know his will. We are zealous for true worship.—[1 Tim. 4:16].

17 As Jehovah’s people, we have been blessed with the knowledge of the truth about God’s purpose for mankind and the earth. We have the means to help people find happiness and a sure hope for the future. We can point them to the way to stay safe when destruction comes upon Satan’s system of things. (2 Thess. 1:7-9) Rather than feel frustrated or discouraged because Jehovah’s day seems to be delayed, we should be glad that there is still time for us to be zealous for true worship. ([Mic. 7:7;][Hab. 2:3]) How can we develop such zeal? We will consider this in the following article.

^ par. 2 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ par. 2 (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”*

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ par. 2 (Mark 13:10) Also, in all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.

^ par. 2 (Matt. 9:37) Then he said to his disciples: “Yes, the harvest is great, but the workers are few.

^ par. 3 (Luke 18:28-30) But Peter said: “Look! We have left what was ours and followed you.” 29 He said to them: “Truly I say to you, there is no one who has left house or wife or brothers or parents or children for the sake of the Kingdom of God 30 who will not get many times more in this period of time, and in the coming system of things,* everlasting life.”

Or “the coming age.” See Glossary.

^ par. 3 (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ par. 4 (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence* and of the conclusion of the system of things?”*

See Glossary.

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ par. 4 (Matt. 24:33) Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors.

^ par. 4 (2 Tim. 3:1-5) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. 2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal, 3 having no natural affection, not open to any agreement, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, without love of goodness, 4 betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God, 5 having an appearance of godliness but proving false to its power; and from these turn away.

^ par. 4 (Matt. 24:36) “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.

^ par. 4 (Prov. 13:12) Expectation* postponed makes the heart sick, But a desire realized is a tree of life.

Or “Hope.”

^ par. 5 (Matt. 9:35) And Jesus set out on a tour of all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues and preaching the good news of the Kingdom and curing every sort of disease and every sort of infirmity.

^ par. 5 (John 18:37) So Pilate said to him: “Well, then, are you a king?” Jesus answered: “You yourself are saying that I am a king. For this I have been born, and for this I have come into the world, that I should bear witness to the truth. Everyone who is on the side of the truth listens to my voice.”

^ par. 6 (Dan. 9:27) “And he will keep the covenant in force for the many for one week; and at the half of the week, he will cause sacrifice and gift offering to cease. “And on the wing of disgusting things there will be the one causing desolation; and until an extermination, what was decided on will be poured out also on the one lying desolate.”

^ par. 6 (John 12:23) But Jesus answered them: “The hour has come for the Son of man to be glorified.

^ par. 6 (John 14:12) Most truly I say to you, whoever exercises faith in me will also do the works that I do; and he will do works greater than these, because I am going my way to the Father.

^ par. 7 (John 2:13-17) Now the Passover of the Jews was near, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. 14 He found in the temple those selling cattle and sheep and doves, and the money brokers in their seats. 15 So after making a whip of ropes, he drove all those with the sheep and cattle out of the temple, and he poured out the coins of the money changers and overturned their tables. 16 And he said to those selling the doves: “Take these things away from here! Stop making the house of my Father a house of commerce!”* 17 His disciples recalled that it is written: “The zeal for your house will consume me.”

Or “a marketplace; a business.”

^ par. 8 (Ps. 69:9) Zeal for your house has consumed me, And the reproaches of those reproaching you have fallen upon me.

^ par. 10 (Ex. 20:5) You must not bow down to them nor be enticed to serve them, for I, Jehovah your God, am a God who requires exclusive devotion, bringing punishment for the error of fathers upon sons, upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation of those who hate me,

^ par. 10 (Ex. 34:14) You must not bow down to another god, for Jehovah is known for* requiring exclusive devotion.* Yes, he is a God who requires exclusive devotion.

Lit., “Jehovah, his name is.”

Or “not tolerating rivals.”

^ par. 10 (Josh. 24:19) Then Joshua said to the people: “You are not able to serve Jehovah, for he is a holy God; he is a God who requires exclusive devotion. He will not pardon your transgressions* and your sins.

Or “rebellion.”

^ par. 11 (Matt. 9:36) On seeing the crowds, he felt pity for them, because they were skinned and thrown about like sheep without a shepherd.

^ par. 11 (Matt. 23:2) “The scribes and the Pharisees have seated themselves in the seat of Moses.

^ par. 11 (Matt. 23:4) They bind up heavy loads and put them on the shoulders of men, but they themselves are not willing to budge them with their finger.

^ par. 11 (Matt. 23:27, 28) “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you resemble whitewashed graves, which outwardly indeed appear beautiful but inside are full of dead men’s bones and of every sort of uncleanness. 28 In the same way, on the outside you appear righteous to men, but inside you are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness.

^ par. 11 (Matt. 23:33) “Serpents, offspring of vipers, how will you flee from the judgment of Ge·henʹna?*

See Glossary.

^ par. 12 (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.*

Or “be held sacred; be treated as holy.”

^ par. 12 (Rom. 2:21-24) do you, however, the one teaching someone else, not teach yourself? You, the one preaching, “Do not steal,” do you steal? 22 You, the one saying, “Do not commit adultery,” do you commit adultery? You, the one abhorring idols, do you rob temples? 23 You who take pride in law, do you dishonor God by your transgressing of the Law? 24 For “the name of God is being blasphemed among the nations because of you,” just as it is written.

^ par. 12 (Jas. 4:7, 8) Therefore, subject yourselves to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you. 8 Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ par. 13 (Matt. 6:10) Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

^ par. 14 (John 17:17) Sanctify them* by means of the truth; your word is truth.

Or “Set them apart; Make them holy.”

^ par. 14 (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Or “wise.”

^ par. 14 (2 Tim. 4:3, 4) For there will be a period of time when they will not put up with the wholesome* teaching, but according to their own desires, they will surround themselves with teachers to have their ears tickled.* 4 They will turn away from listening to the truth and give attention to false stories.

Or “healthful; beneficial.”

Or “to tell them what they want to hear.”

^ par. 15 (Matt. 9:36) On seeing the crowds, he felt pity for them, because they were skinned and thrown about like sheep without a shepherd.

^ par. 15 (Mark 6:34) Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

^ par. 16 (1 Tim. 2:3, 4) This is fine and acceptable in the sight of our Savior, God, 4 whose will is that all sorts of people should be saved and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.

^ par. 16 (1 Tim. 4:16) Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Persevere in these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

^ par. 17 (2 Thess. 1:7-9) But you who suffer tribulation will be given relief along with us at the revelation of the Lord Jesus from heaven with his powerful angels 8 in a flaming fire, as he brings vengeance on those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus. 9 These very ones will undergo the judicial punishment of everlasting destruction from before the Lord and from the glory of his strength,

^ par. 17 (Mic. 7:7) But as for me, I will keep on the lookout for Jehovah. I will show a waiting attitude* for the God of my salvation. My God will hear me.

Or “I will wait patiently.”

^ par. 17 (Hab. 2:3) For the vision is yet for its appointed time, And it is rushing toward its end,* and it will not lie. Even if it should delay,* keep in expectation of it!* For it will without fail come true. It will not be late!

Or “fulfillment.”

Or “if it seems to delay.”

Or “wait eagerly for it!”

^ ***w14 1/15 pp. 23-24 Serving Jehovah Before the Days of Distress Come***

4. What question can Christians with long experience ask themselves, and why?

4 If you have acquired decades of experience as an adult, you have a key question to ask yourself, ‘What will I do with my life now while I still have some energy and strength?’ As an experienced Christian, you have opportunities that are not open to others. You can pass on to younger ones what you have learned from Jehovah. You can strengthen others by relating experiences you have enjoyed while serving God. King David prayed for opportunities to do so. He wrote: “O God, you have taught me from my youth . . . Even when I am old and gray, O God, do not abandon me. Let me tell the next generation about your power and about your mightiness to all those who are to come.”—Ps. 71:17, 18.

5. How can older Christians pass on to others what they have learned?

5 How could you make known the wisdom you have acquired over the years? Could you invite younger servants of God to your home for some upbuilding association? Could you ask them to accompany you in the Christian ministry and show them the joy you experience in serving Jehovah? Elihu of ancient times said: “Let age speak, and let a multitude of years declare wisdom.” ([Job 32:7]) The apostle Paul urged experienced Christian women to encourage others by word and example. He wrote: “Let the older women be . . . teachers of what is good.”—[Titus 2:3].

CONSIDER YOUR POTENTIAL FOR HELPING OTHERS

6. Why should Christians with decades of experience not underestimate their potential?

6 If you are an experienced Christian, you have great potential. Consider what you understand now that you did not know 30 or 40 years ago. You can skillfully apply Bible principles in life. No doubt you have the ability to reach the hearts of others with Bible truth. If you are an elder, you know how to help brothers who take a false step. ([Gal. 6:1]) Perhaps you have learned how to oversee congregation activities, assembly departments, or Kingdom Hall construction. You may know how to encourage doctors to use health-care strategies that avoid the use of blood. Even if you have only recently learned the truth, you have valuable experience in life. For example, if you have raised children, you will have gained much practical wisdom. Older Christians are a potentially powerful source of encouragement for Jehovah’s people by teaching, leading, and strengthening the brothers and sisters.—Read Job 12:12.

7. What useful training can older Christians provide for younger ones?

7 How could you use your potential more fully? Perhaps you could show younger ones how to start and conduct Bible studies. If you are a sister, could you suggest to young mothers how they might keep up with spiritual activities while caring for small children? If you are a brother, could you teach young brothers to give talks with enthusiasm and to be more effective preachers of the good news? Could you show them how you visit elderly brothers and sisters to encourage them spiritually? Even if you do not have the physical power that you used to have, you have splendid opportunities to train younger ones. God’s Word says: “The glory of young men is their strength, and the splendor of old men is their gray hair.”—[Prov. 20:29].

SERVING WHERE THE NEED IS GREATER

8. What did the apostle Paul do later in life?

8 The apostle Paul used his full potential to serve God later in life. By the time he was released from prison in Rome about 61 C.E., he had endured many years of rigorous missionary service, and he could have settled down to preach in Rome. (2 Cor. 11:23-27) The brothers in that large city would no doubt have valued his continued support. But Paul saw that the need was even greater overseas. With Timothy and Titus, he resumed his missionary activity, traveling to Ephesus, then on to Crete, and probably to Macedonia. ([1 Tim. 1:3;][Titus 1:5]) We do not know if he visited Spain, but he intended to do so.—[Rom. 15:24,][28].

9. When may Peter have moved to serve where the need was greater? (See opening image.)

9 The apostle Peter may have been over 50 when he moved to where the need was greater. Why may that be true? If he was about the same age as Jesus or perhaps somewhat older, he would have been about 50 years old when he met with the other apostles in Jerusalem in the year 49 C.E. ([Acts 15:7]) Some time after that meeting, Peter went to live in Babylon, doubtless to preach to the large population of Jews in that area. ([Gal. 2:9]) He was residing there when he wrote his first inspired letter, about 62 C.E. ([1 Pet. 5:13]) Settling in a foreign land can be challenging, but Peter did not allow the fact that he was advancing in age to rob him of the joy of serving Jehovah fully.

10, 11. Relate an experience about someone who later in life moved to serve where the need is greater.

10 Today, many Christians in their 50’s and older find that their circumstances have changed and that they are able to serve Jehovah in new ways. Some have moved to where the need is greater. For example, Robert writes: “My wife and I were in our mid-50’s when we realized what opportunities lay before us. Our only son had left home, we no longer had aging parents needing care, and we had received a small inheritance. I calculated that the sale of our house would suffice to pay off the mortgage and provide for us until I received income from my retirement pension. We heard that in Bolivia the number of people accepting Bible studies is high but the cost of living is low. So we decided to move. Adapting to our new home was not easy. Everything was so different from what we were accustomed to in North America. But our efforts were well rewarded.”

^ par. 4 (Ps. 71:17, 18) O God, you have taught me from my youth, And until now I keep declaring your wonderful works. 18 Even when I am old and gray, O God, do not abandon me. Let me tell the next generation about your power* And about your mightiness to all those who are to come.

Lit., “arm.”

^ par. 5 (Job 32:7) I thought, ‘Let age* speak, And let a multitude of years declare wisdom.’

Lit., “days.”

^ par. 5 (Titus 2:3) Likewise, let the older women be reverent in behavior, not slanderous, not enslaved to a lot of wine, teachers of what is good,

^ par. 6 (Gal. 6:1) Brothers, even if a man takes a false step before he is aware of it, you who have spiritual qualifications try to readjust such a man in a spirit of mildness. But keep an eye on yourself, for fear you too may be tempted.

^ par. 6 (Job 12:12) Is not wisdom found among the aged, And does not understanding come with a long life?

^ par. 7 (Prov. 20:29) The glory of young men is their strength, And the splendor of old men is their gray hair.

^ par. 8 (2 Cor. 11:23-27) Are they ministers of Christ? I reply like a madman, I am more outstandingly one: I have done more work, been imprisoned more often, suffered countless beatings, and experienced many near-deaths. 24 Five times I received 40 strokes less one from the Jews, 25 three times I was beaten with rods, once I was stoned, three times I experienced shipwreck, a night and a day I have spent in the open sea; 26 in journeys often, in dangers from rivers, in dangers from robbers, in dangers from my own people, in dangers from the nations, in dangers in the city, in dangers in the wilderness, in dangers at sea, in dangers among false brothers, 27 in labor and toil, in sleepless nights often, in hunger and thirst, frequently without food, in cold and lacking clothing.*

Lit., “and in nakedness.”

^ par. 8 (1 Tim. 1:3) Just as I encouraged you to stay in Ephʹe·sus when I was about to go to Mac·e·doʹni·a, so I do now, in order for you to command certain ones not to teach different doctrine,

^ par. 8 (Titus 1:5) I left you in Crete so that you would correct the things that were defective* and make appointments of elders in city after city, as I instructed you:

Or “deficient.”

^ par. 8 (Rom. 15:24) Therefore, when I journey to Spain, I hope that I will see you and be accompanied partway there by you after I have first enjoyed your company for a time.

^ par. 8 (Rom. 15:28) So after I have finished with this and have delivered this contribution* securely to them, I will depart by way of you for Spain.

Lit., “fruit.”

^ par. 9 (Acts 15:7) After much intense discussion* had taken place, Peter rose and said to them: “Men, brothers, you well know that from early days God made the choice among you that through my mouth people of the nations should hear the word of the good news and believe.

Or “much disputing.”

^ par. 9 (Gal. 2:9) and when they recognized the undeserved kindness that was given me, James and Ceʹphas* and John, the ones who seemed to be pillars, gave Barʹna·bas and me the right hand of fellowship,* so that we should go to the nations but they to those who are circumcised.

Also called Peter.

Or “partnership.”

^ par. 9 (1 Pet. 5:13) She who is in Babylon, a chosen one like you, sends you her greetings, and so does Mark, my son.

^ ***w15 10/1 p. 16 par. 3 Bible Questions Answered***

Who can eliminate poverty?

God has appointed his Son, Jesus, to rule over all mankind. ([Psalm 2:4-8]) Jesus will rescue the poor and bring an end to oppression and violence.—Read Psalm 72:8, 12-14.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 2:4-8) The One enthroned in the heavens will laugh; Jehovah will scoff at them.  5 At that time he will speak to them in his anger And terrify them in his burning anger,  6 Saying: “I myself have installed my king On Zion, my holy mountain.”  7 Let me proclaim the decree of Jehovah; He said to me: “You are my son; Today I have become your father.  8 Ask of me, and I will give nations as your inheritance And the ends of the earth as your possession.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 72:8) He will have subjects* from sea to sea And from the River* to the ends of the earth.

Or “will rule.”

That is, the Euphrates.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 72:12-14) For he will rescue the poor who cry for help, Also the lowly one and whoever has no helper. 13 He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save. 14 From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes.

Or “souls.”

Or “redeem their souls.”

^ ***w10 8/15 p. 32 Who Can Deliver Those Crying for Help?***

A New World of Plenty Awaits Us

19, 20. (a) As indicated in [Psalm 72], what problem will be solved by Kingdom rule? (b) To whom should primary credit go for Christ’s rule, and how do you feel about what it will accomplish?

19 Try again to visualize the future of upright humans in God’s new world under the rule of the Greater Solomon. “There will come to be plenty of grain on the earth,” we are promised. “On the top of the mountains there will be an overflow.” ([Ps. 72:16]) Since grain is not ordinarily produced on mountain tops, these words emphasize how productive the earth will become. Its produce “will be as in Lebanon,” a region that produced abundantly at the time of Solomon’s reign. Just think! No more food shortages, no one undernourished, nobody starving! All will then enjoy “a banquet of well-oiled dishes.”—[Isa. 25:6-8;][35:1, 2].

20 To whom will credit go for all these blessings? Primarily to the Eternal King and Universal Ruler, Jehovah God. In effect, all of us will then joyfully add our voices to the concluding portion of this beautiful and heartwarming song: “Let his name [that of the King Jesus Christ] prove to be to time indefinite; before the sun let his name have increase, and by means of him let them bless themselves; let all nations pronounce him happy. Blessed be Jehovah God, Israel’s God, who alone is doing wonderful works. And blessed be his glorious name to time indefinite, and let his glory fill the whole earth. Amen and Amen.”—[Ps. 72:17-19].

^ (Ps. 72:0-20) Regarding Solomon. 72 O God, give your judgments to the king, And endow the son of the king with your righteousness.  2 May he plead the cause of your people with righteousness, And of your lowly ones with justice.  3 May the mountains bring peace to the people, And may the hills bring righteousness.  4 Let him defend* the lowly among the people, Let him save the sons of the poor, And let him crush the defrauder.  5 They will fear you as long as there is a sun And as long as the moon remains, For generation after generation.  6 He will be like the rain that falls on the mown grass, Like showers of rain that water the earth.  7 In his days the righteous will flourish,* And peace will abound until the moon is no more.  8 He will have subjects* from sea to sea And from the River* to the ends of the earth.  9 The desert dwellers will bow down before him, And his enemies will lick the dust. 10 The kings of Tarʹshish and of the islands will pay tribute. The kings of Sheʹba and of Seʹba will present gifts. 11 All the kings will bow down before him, And all the nations will serve him. 12 For he will rescue the poor who cry for help, Also the lowly one and whoever has no helper. 13 He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save. 14 From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes. 15 May he live and be given the gold of Sheʹba. May prayers be said for him continually, And may he be blessed all day long. 16 There will be an abundance of grain on the earth; On the top of the mountains it will overflow. His fruit will flourish as in Lebʹa·non, And in the cities people will blossom like the vegetation of the earth. 17 May his name endure forever, And may it prosper as long as the sun. May people obtain a blessing for themselves by means of him; May all nations pronounce him happy. 18 May Jehovah God be praised, Israel’s God, Who alone does wonderful things. 19 May his glorious name be praised forever, And may his glory fill the whole earth. Amen and Amen. 20 This completes the prayers of David, the son of Jesʹse.

Lit., “judge.”

Lit., “sprout.”

Or “will rule.”

That is, the Euphrates.

Or “souls.”

Or “redeem their souls.”

^ par. 19 (Ps. 72:16) There will be an abundance of grain on the earth; On the top of the mountains it will overflow. His fruit will flourish as in Lebʹa·non, And in the cities people will blossom like the vegetation of the earth.

^ par. 19 (Isa. 25:6-8) In this mountain Jehovah of armies will make for all the peoples A banquet of rich dishes, A banquet of fine wine,* Of rich dishes filled with marrow, Of fine, filtered wine.  7 In this mountain he will do away with* the shroud that is enveloping all the peoples And the covering* that is woven over all the nations.  8 He will swallow up* death forever, And the Sovereign Lord Jehovah will wipe away the tears from all faces. The reproach of his people he will take away from all the earth, For Jehovah himself has spoken it.

Or “of wine kept on the dregs.”

Lit., “swallow up.”

Or “veil.”

Or “do away with.”

^ par. 19 (Isa. 35:1, 2) The wilderness and the parched land will exult, And the desert plain will be joyful and blossom as the saffron.*  2 Without fail it will blossom; It will rejoice and shout for joy. The glory of Lebʹa·non will be given to it, The splendor of Carʹmel and of Sharʹon. They will see the glory of Jehovah, the splendor of our God.

Or “crocus.”

^ par. 20 (Ps. 72:17-19) May his name endure forever, And may it prosper as long as the sun. May people obtain a blessing for themselves by means of him; May all nations pronounce him happy. 18 May Jehovah God be praised, Israel’s God, Who alone does wonderful things. 19 May his glorious name be praised forever, And may his glory fill the whole earth. Amen and Amen.

^ ***w11 8/15 p. 11 They Waited for the Messiah***

17. John made what application of [Psalm 69:4]?

17 The Messiah would be hated without cause. ([Ps. 69:4]) The apostle John quotes Jesus as saying: “If I had not done among [the people] the works that no one else did, they would have no sin; but now they have both seen and hated me as well as my Father. But it is that the word written in their Law may be fulfilled, ‘They hated me without cause.’” (John 15:24, 25) Often the “Law” means the whole body of Scripture. ([John 10:34;][12:34]) The Gospel accounts prove that Jesus was hated, especially by the Jewish religious leaders. Moreover, Christ said: “The world has no reason to hate you, but it hates me, because I bear witness concerning it that its works are wicked.”—[John 7:7].

^ (Ps. 69:4) Those hating me without cause Are more numerous than the hairs of my head. Those who would do away with me, My treacherous enemies,* have become many. I was forced to hand over what I had not stolen.

Or “enemies for no reason.”

^ par. 17 (Ps. 69:4) Those hating me without cause Are more numerous than the hairs of my head. Those who would do away with me, My treacherous enemies,* have become many. I was forced to hand over what I had not stolen.

Or “enemies for no reason.”

^ par. 17 (John 15:24, 25) If I had not done among them the works that no one else did, they would have no sin; but now they have both seen me and hated me as well as my Father. 25 But this happened in order to fulfill the word written in their Law: ‘They hated me without cause.’

^ par. 17 (John 10:34) Jesus answered them: “Is it not written in your Law, ‘I said: “You are gods”’?*

Or “godlike ones.”

^ par. 17 (John 12:34) Then the crowd answered him: “We heard from the Law that the Christ remains forever. How can you say that the Son of man must be lifted up? Who is this Son of man?”

^ par. 17 (John 7:7) The world has no reason to hate you, but it hates me, because I bear witness about it that its works are wicked.

^ ***w11 8/15 p. 15 They Found the Messiah!***

15 The Messiah would be given vinegar and gall. “For food they gave me a poisonous plant,” said the psalmist, “and for my thirst they tried to make me drink vinegar.” ([Ps. 69:21]) Matthew tells us: “They gave [Jesus] wine mixed with gall to drink; but, after tasting it, he refused to drink.” Later, “one of them ran and took a sponge and soaked it with sour wine and put it on a reed and went giving him a drink.”—[Matt. 27:34,][48].

^ par. 15 (Ps. 69:21) But for food they gave me poison,* And for my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink.

Or “a poisonous plant.”

^ par. 15 (Matt. 27:34) they gave him wine mixed with gall* to drink; but after tasting it, he refused to drink it.

A bitter liquid.

^ par. 15 (Matt. 27:48) And immediately one of them ran and took a sponge and soaked it in sour wine and put it on a reed and gave it to him to drink.

^ ***w13 2/15 pp. 25-26 Let Nothing Hinder You From Taking Hold of Glory***

3-5. To what glory may Jehovah lead us?

3 The psalmist expressed confidence that Jehovah would take hold of him by the right hand and lead him to genuine glory. (Read Psalm 73:23, 24.) How does Jehovah do this? Jehovah leads his humble servants to glory by honoring them in numerous ways. He blesses them with an understanding of his will. ([1 Cor. 2:7]) He bestows upon those who listen to his word and obey him the honor of a close personal relationship with him.—[Jas. 4:8].

4 Jehovah also entrusts his servants with the glorious treasure of the Christian ministry. ([2 Cor. 4:1,][7]) And this ministry leads to glory. To those who use their privilege of service to his praise and to the benefit of others, Jehovah promises: “Those honoring me I shall honor.” ([1 Sam. 2:30]) Such ones are honored with a good name with Jehovah, and they are likely to be well spoken of by other servants of God.—[Prov. 11:16;][22:1].

^ par. 3 (Ps. 73:23, 24) But now I am continually with you; You have taken hold of my right hand. 24 You guide me with your advice, And afterward you will lead me to glory.

^ par. 3 (1 Cor. 2:7) But we speak God’s wisdom in a sacred secret, the hidden wisdom, which God foreordained before the systems of things for our glory.

^ par. 3 (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ par. 4 (2 Cor. 4:1) Therefore, since we have this ministry through the mercy that was shown us, we do not give up.

^ par. 4 (2 Cor. 4:7) However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels,* so that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not from us.

Or “in jars of clay.”

^ par. 4 (1 Sam. 2:30) “‘That is why the word of Jehovah the God of Israel is: “I did indeed say that your house and the house of your forefather would always walk before me.” But now Jehovah declares: “It is unthinkable, on my part, because those honoring me I will honor, but those despising me will be treated with contempt.”

^ par. 4 (Prov. 11:16) A gracious* woman acquires glory, But ruthless men seize riches.

Or “charming.”

^ par. 4 (Prov. 22:1) A good name* is to be chosen rather than great wealth; To be respected* is better than silver and gold.

Or “A good reputation.” Lit., “A name.”

Lit., “Favor.”

^ ***fg lesson 5***

Adam and Eve disobeyed God, so Jehovah put them out of the garden. Paradise was lost, and no man has succeeded in restoring it. The Bible says: “The earth has been handed over to the wicked.”—[Job 9:24].—Read Genesis 3:23, 24.

Has Jehovah abandoned his original purpose for mankind? No! He is almighty. He cannot fail. ([Isaiah 45:18]) He will restore the human race to the way he meant it to be.—Read Psalm 37:11, 34.

^ par. 3 (Job 9:24) The earth has been handed over to the wicked; He covers the eyes* of its judges. If it is not he, then, who is it?

Lit., “faces.”

^ par. 3 (Gen. 3:23, 24) With that Jehovah God expelled him from the garden of Eʹden to cultivate the ground from which he had been taken. 24 So he drove the man out, and he posted at the east of the garden of Eʹden the cherubs and the flaming blade of a sword that was turning continuously to guard the way to the tree of life.

^ par. 4 (Isa. 45:18) For this is what Jehovah says, The Creator of the heavens, the true God, The One who formed the earth, its Maker who firmly established it, Who did not create it simply for nothing,* but formed it to be inhabited: “I am Jehovah, and there is no one else.

Or possibly, “to be empty.”

^ par. 4 (Ps. 37:11) But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

^ par. 4 (Ps. 37:34) Hope in Jehovah and follow his way, And he will exalt you to take possession of the earth. When the wicked are done away with, you will see it.

^ ***snnw song 140 The Life of a Pioneer***

Song 140

The Life of a Pioneer

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(Ecclesiastes 11:6)

At the start of the day, with the sun yet to rise,

We are making our way

with the sleep in our eyes,

and we pray.

We are there with a smile for the people we meet.

Some may stop for a while,

some pass by on the street, but we stay.

(CHORUS)

It’s the life that we choose;

For Jehovah we live.

And whatever he asks, we will do.

In the work we endure,

Whether sunshine or rain.

It’s a way we can say ev’ry day:

“I love you.”

At the end of the day, with the sun sinking low,

Feeling happy and tired,

in our heart there’s a glow,

and we pray.

It’s a life that we love, always giving our best.

And Jehovah we thank,

for by him we are blessed ev’ry day.

(CHORUS)

It’s the life that we choose;

For Jehovah we live.

And whatever he asks, we will do.

In the work we endure,

Whether sunshine or rain.

It’s a way we can say ev’ry day:

“I love you.”

(See also [Josh. 24:15;][Ps. 92:2;][Rom. 14:8].)

^ (Eccl. 11:6) Sow your seed in the morning and do not let your hand rest until the evening; for you do not know which will have success, whether this one or that one, or whether they will both do well.

^ (Josh. 24:15) Now if it seems bad to you to serve Jehovah, choose for yourselves today whom you will serve, whether the gods that your forefathers served on the other side of the River* or the gods of the Amʹor·ites in whose land you are dwelling. But as for me and my household, we will serve Jehovah.”

That is, the Euphrates.

^ (Ps. 92:2) To declare your loyal love in the morning And your faithfulness during the nights,

^ (Rom. 14:8) For if we live, we live to Jehovah,* and if we die, we die to Jehovah.* So both if we live and if we die, we belong to Jehovah.*

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ ***ia pp. 166-171 He Protected, He Provided, He Persevered***

17, 18. (a) What did Jesus learn from his adoptive father? (b) Why did Joseph have to work ever harder at his trade?

17 Imagine Jesus as a small boy watching his adoptive father at work. His eyes wide and intent on Joseph’s every movement, he no doubt admired the strength in those broad shoulders and sinewy arms, the skill of the hands, the intelligence in the eyes. Perhaps Joseph began showing his young son how to perform such simple tasks as using dried fish skin to smooth out rough spots on wood. He likely taught Jesus the differences between the varieties of wood that he used—the sycamore fig, oak, or olive, for example.

18 Jesus learned, too, that those strong hands that felled trees, hewed beams, and pounded joints together were also gentle hands that caressed and comforted him, his mother, and his siblings. Yes, Joseph and Mary had a growing family that eventually included at least six children in addition to Jesus. (Matt. 13:55, 56) Joseph had to work ever harder to care for and feed them all.

Joseph understood that caring for his family’s spiritual needs was paramount

19. How did Joseph care for his family’s spiritual needs?

19 Joseph, however, understood that caring for his family’s spiritual needs was paramount. So he spent time teaching his children about Jehovah God and His laws. He and Mary regularly took them to the local synagogue, where the Law was read aloud and explained. Perhaps Jesus was full of questions afterward, and Joseph tried hard to satisfy the boy’s spiritual hunger. Joseph also took his family to religious festivals in Jerusalem. For the annual Passover, Joseph may have needed two weeks to make the 75-mile journey (120 km), observe the occasion, and return home.

20. How can Christian family heads follow the pattern set by Joseph?

20 Christian family heads today follow a similar pattern. They give of themselves for their children, putting spiritual training above every other concern, including material comforts. They go to great lengths to conduct family worship at home and to take their children to Christian meetings both large and small. Like Joseph, they know that there is no better investment they can make for the sake of their children.

“In Mental Distress”

21. What was Passover time like for Joseph’s family, and when did Joseph and Mary notice that Jesus was missing?

21 When Jesus was 12 years old, Joseph took the family to Jerusalem as usual. It was Passover, a festive time, and large families traveled together in long caravans through the lush spring countryside. As they approached the starker landscapes near lofty Jerusalem, many would sing the familiar psalms of ascent. ([Ps. 120-134]) The city likely teemed with hundreds of thousands of people. Afterward, the families and their caravans began to head homeward. Joseph and Mary, perhaps with much to do, assumed that Jesus was traveling with others, maybe family members. Only after Jerusalem lay a full day behind them did they realize a terrifying truth—Jesus was missing!—[Luke 2:41-44].

22, 23. What did Joseph and Mary do about their missing boy, and what did Mary say when they finally found him?

22 Frantically, they retraced their steps all the way to Jerusalem. Imagine how empty and strange the city seemed to them now as they paced the streets, calling out their son’s name. Where could the boy be? By the third day of searching, did Joseph begin to wonder if he had failed terribly in this sacred trust from Jehovah? Finally, they went to the temple. There they searched until they came upon a chamber where many learned men, versed in the Law, were gathered—with young Jesus sitting among them! Imagine the relief Joseph and Mary felt!—Luke 2:45, 46.

23 Jesus was listening to the learned men and eagerly asking questions. The men were amazed at the child’s understanding and his answers. Mary and Joseph, though, were astounded. In the Bible record, Joseph is silent. But Mary’s words speak eloquently for both of them: “Child, why did you treat us this way? Here your father and I in mental distress have been looking for you.”—Luke 2:47, 48.

24. How does the Bible paint a realistic picture of parenthood?

24 Thus in a few deft strokes, God’s Word paints a realistic picture of parenthood. It can be stressful—even when the child is perfect! Parenting in today’s dangerous world can bring untold “mental distress,” but fathers and mothers can take comfort in knowing that the Bible acknowledges the challenge they face.

25, 26. How did Jesus answer his parents, and how might Joseph have felt about his son’s words?

25 Jesus had stayed in the one place in the world where he felt the closest to his heavenly Father, Jehovah, eagerly soaking up anything he could learn. He answered his parents in simple sincerity: “Why did you have to go looking for me? Did you not know that I must be in the house of my Father?”—[Luke 2:49].

26 Joseph surely thought about those words many times. Perhaps he came to beam with pride over them. After all, he had worked diligently to teach his adopted son to feel that way about Jehovah God. By that time in his life as a boy, Jesus already had warm feelings about the word “father”—feelings shaped largely by his years with Joseph.

27. As a father, how are you privileged, and why should you remember Joseph’s example?

27 If you are a father, do you realize how privileged you are to help your children to form a concept of what a loving, protective father is? Likewise, if you have stepchildren or adopted children, remember Joseph’s example and treat each child as unique and precious. Help those children to draw closer to their heavenly Father, Jehovah God.—Read Ephesians 6:4.

Joseph Persevered Faithfully

28, 29. (a) What do the words recorded at Luke 2:51, 52 reveal about Joseph? (b) Joseph played what role in helping his son progress in wisdom?

28 The Bible discloses only a few more traces of Joseph’s life, but they are worth considering carefully. We read that Jesus “continued subject to them”—his parents. We also find that “Jesus went on progressing in wisdom and in physical growth and in favor with God and men.” (Read Luke 2:51, 52.) What do those words reveal about Joseph? Several things. We learn that Joseph continued taking the lead in his household, for his perfect son respected his father’s authority and remained in subjection to it.

29 We further learn that Jesus continued to grow in wisdom. Joseph surely had much to do with his son’s progress in that regard. In those days, there was a time-honored proverb among the Jews. It can still be found and read today. The saying asserts that only men of leisure can become truly wise, whereas tradesmen, such as carpenters, farmers, and blacksmiths, “cannot declare justice and judgment; and they shall not be found where parables are spoken.” Later, Jesus exposed the emptiness of that proverb. As a boy, how often he had heard his adoptive father, humble carpenter though he was, teach effectively about Jehovah’s “justice and judgment”! No doubt, there were countless occasions.

30. How did Joseph set an example for family heads today?

30 We can also see evidence of Joseph’s influence in Jesus’ physical growth. A well-cared-for boy, Jesus grew into a strong, healthy man. Further, Joseph trained his son to be skilled at his physical work. Jesus was known not only as the carpenter’s son but also as “the carpenter.” ([Mark 6:3]) So Joseph’s training was successful. Family heads wisely imitate Joseph, caring for the practical well-being of their children and ensuring that they can support themselves.

31. (a) What does evidence suggest regarding the end of Joseph’s life? (Include the box.) (b) What example did Joseph leave for us to imitate?

31 Once we reach the point in the Bible record where Jesus is baptized at about the age of 30, we find that Joseph is no longer part of the story. Evidence suggests that Mary was a widow by the time Jesus began his ministry. (See the box “When Did Joseph Die?”) Yet, Joseph left a clear mark—a shining example of a father who protected his family, provided for them, and persevered faithfully to the end. Any father, any family head, or any other Christian would do well to imitate the faith of Joseph.

When Did Joseph Die?

We know that Joseph was alive when Jesus was 12 years old. At that age many Jewish youths began to learn their father’s trade and became apprentices at 15. Joseph evidently lived long enough to teach Jesus to be a carpenter. Was Joseph still living when Jesus began his ministry at about 30 years of age? That seems very doubtful. Jesus’ mother, brothers, and sisters are all mentioned as living at that time but not Joseph. Jesus was once even called “the son of Mary,” not the son of Joseph. ([Mark 6:3]) Mary is spoken of as acting and taking initiatives on her own, without consulting a husband. ([John 2:1-5]) That would have been unusual in Bible times unless she was a widow. Finally, as he was dying, Jesus entrusted the care of his mother to the apostle John. (John 19:26, 27) There would have been no need to do so if Joseph were still living. Likely, then, Joseph died when Jesus was still a relatively young man. As the eldest son, Jesus undoubtedly took over the carpentry business and cared for the family until his baptism.

^ par. 18 (Matt. 13:55, 56) Is this not the carpenter’s son? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brothers James and Joseph and Simon and Judas? 56 And his sisters, are they not all with us? Where, then, did he get all of this?”

^ par. 21 (Pss. 120:0-134:3) A Song of the Ascents.* 120 I called to Jehovah in my distress, And he answered me.  2 O Jehovah, rescue me* from lying lips And from the deceitful tongue.  3 What will He do to you, and how will He punish you,* You deceitful tongue?  4 With sharp arrows of a warrior And burning coals of broomwood.  5 Woe to me, for I have lived as a foreigner in Meʹshech! I have been dwelling among the tents of Keʹdar.  6 I have* been dwelling far too long With those who hate peace.  7 I am for peace, but when I speak, They are for war.

A Song of the Ascents. 121 I raise my eyes to the mountains. From where will my help come?  2 My help comes from Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth.  3 He will never allow your foot to slip.* The One guarding you will never be drowsy.  4 Look! He will never be drowsy nor go to sleep, The One guarding Israel.  5 Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is the shade at your right hand.  6 By day the sun will not strike you, Nor the moon by night.  7 Jehovah will guard you against all harm. He will guard your life.*  8 Jehovah will guard you in all you do* From now on and forever.

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 122 I rejoiced when they said to me: “Let us go to the house of Jehovah.”  2 And now our feet are standing Within your gates, O Jerusalem.  3 Jerusalem is built as a city That is joined together as one.  4 The tribes have gone up to it, The tribes of Jah,* According to the reminder to Israel, To give thanks to the name of Jehovah.  5 For thrones for judgment were set up there, Thrones of the house of David.  6 Ask for the peace of Jerusalem. Those who love you, O city, will be secure.  7 May peace continue within your ramparts,* Security within your fortified towers.  8 For the sake of my brothers and my companions I will say: “May there be peace within you.”  9 For the sake of the house of Jehovah our God, I will seek good for you.

A Song of the Ascents. 123 To you I raise my eyes, You who are enthroned in the heavens.  2 As the eyes of servants look to the hand of their master, And the eyes of a servant girl to the hand of her mistress, So our eyes look to Jehovah our God Until he shows us favor.  3 Show us favor, O Jehovah, show us favor, For we have had our full share of contempt.  4 We have had our full share of* ridicule from the self-assured And the contempt of the arrogant.

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 124 “If Jehovah had not been with us” —Let Israel now say—  2 “If Jehovah had not been with us When men rose up to attack us,  3 Then they would have swallowed us up alive When their anger was burning against us.  4 Then the waters would have washed us away, The torrent would have swept over us.*  5 The raging waters would have overwhelmed us.*  6 May Jehovah be praised, For he has not given us as prey to their teeth.  7 We are* like a bird that escaped From the hunter’s trap; The trap was broken, And we escaped.  8 Our help is in the name of Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth.”

A Song of the Ascents. 125 Those who trust in Jehovah Are like Mount Zion, which cannot be shaken But endures forever.  2 Just as mountains surround Jerusalem, So Jehovah surrounds his people From now on and forever.  3 The scepter of wickedness will not remain upon the land allotted to the righteous, So that the righteous do not turn to doing* what is wrong.  4 Do good, O Jehovah, to those who are good, To those who are upright in heart.  5 As for those who turn aside to their crooked ways, Jehovah will remove them along with the wrongdoers. May there be peace upon Israel.

A Song of the Ascents. 126 When Jehovah gathered back the captives of Zion, We thought we were dreaming.  2 At that time our mouth was filled with laughter And our tongue with a joyful shout. At that time they said among the nations: “Jehovah has done great things for them.”  3 Jehovah has done great things for us, And we are overjoyed.  4 Do gather back* our captives, O Jehovah, Like streams in the Negʹeb.*  5 Those sowing seed with tears Will reap with a joyful shout.  6 The one who does go out, though weeping, Carrying his bag of seed, Will surely return with a joyful shout, Carrying in his sheaves.

A Song of the Ascents. Of Solomon. 127 Unless Jehovah builds the house, It is in vain that its builders work hard on it. Unless Jehovah guards the city, It is in vain that the guard stays awake.  2 It is in vain that you rise up early, That you stay up late, That you toil for your food, Since he provides for his loved ones while giving them sleep.  3 Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.  4 Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, So are the sons of one’s youth.  5 Happy is the man who fills his quiver with them. They will not be put to shame, For they will speak with enemies in the city gate.

A Song of the Ascents. 128 Happy is everyone who fears Jehovah, Who walks in His ways.  2 You will eat what your hands worked hard to produce. You will be happy and will enjoy prosperity.  3 Your wife will be like a fruitful vine within your house; Your sons will be like shoots of an olive tree around your table.  4 Look! That is how the man who fears Jehovah Will be blessed.  5 Jehovah will bless you from Zion. May you see Jerusalem prosper all the days of your life  6 And see the sons of your sons. May there be peace upon Israel.

A Song of the Ascents. 129 “Since my youth they have constantly attacked me” —Let Israel now say—  2 “Since my youth they have constantly attacked me; But they have not defeated me.  3 Plowmen have plowed across my back; They have made their furrows long.”  4 But Jehovah is righteous; He has cut up the ropes of the wicked.  5 They will be put to shame and will retreat in disgrace, All those who hate Zion.  6 They will become like grass on the rooftops That withers before it is pulled up,  7 That cannot fill the reaper’s hand Nor the arms of the one gathering sheaves.  8 Those passing by will not say: “May the blessing of Jehovah be upon you; We bless you in the name of Jehovah.”

A Song of the Ascents. 130 From the depths I call to you, O Jehovah.  2 O Jehovah, hear my voice. May your ears pay attention to my pleas for help.  3 If errors were what you watch,* O Jah,* Then who, O Jehovah, could stand?  4 For with you there is true forgiveness, So that you may be held in awe.*  5 I hope in Jehovah, my whole being* hopes in him; I wait for his word.  6 I eagerly wait* for Jehovah, More than watchmen wait for the morning, Yes, more than watchmen wait for the morning.  7 Let Israel keep waiting for Jehovah, For Jehovah is loyal in his love, And he has great power to redeem.  8 He will redeem Israel from all their errors.

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 131 O Jehovah, my heart is not haughty, Nor are my eyes lofty; Nor do I aspire to things too great, Or to things that are beyond me.  2 No, but I have calmed and quieted my soul* Like a weaned child with its mother; I am* contented like a weaned child.  3 Let Israel wait for Jehovah From now on and forever.

A Song of the Ascents. 132 O Jehovah, remember David And all his suffering;  2 How he swore to Jehovah, How he vowed to the Powerful One of Jacob:  3 “I will not go into my tent, my home. I will not lie upon my couch, my bed;  4 I will not allow my eyes to sleep, Nor my eyelids to slumber  5 Until I find a place for Jehovah, A fine residence* for the Powerful One of Jacob.”  6 Look! We heard about it in Ephʹra·thah; We found it in the fields of the forest.  7 Let us come into his residence;* Let us bow down at his footstool.  8 Rise up, O Jehovah, to come to your resting-place, You and the Ark of your strength.  9 May your priests be clothed with righteousness, And may your loyal ones shout joyfully. 10 For the sake of David your servant, Do not reject* your anointed one. 11 Jehovah has sworn to David; He will surely not go back on his word: “One of your offspring,* I will place on your throne. 12 If your sons keep my covenant And my reminders that I teach them, Their sons too Will sit on your throne forever.” 13 For Jehovah has chosen Zion; He has desired it for his dwelling place: 14 “This is my resting-place forever; Here I will dwell, for this is my desire. 15 I will richly bless it with provisions; I will satisfy its poor with bread. 16 Its priests I will clothe with salvation, And its loyal ones will shout joyfully. 17 There I will make the strength* of David grow. I have prepared a lamp for my anointed one. 18 I will clothe his enemies with shame, But the crown* on his head will flourish.”

A Song of the Ascents. Of David. 133 Look! How good and how pleasant it is For brothers to dwell together in unity!  2 It is like fine oil poured on the head That runs down the beard, Aaron’s beard, And runs down onto the collar of his garments.  3 It is like the dew of Herʹmon That descends on the mountains of Zion. That is where Jehovah decreed his blessing —Life everlasting.

A Song of the Ascents. 134 Praise Jehovah, All you servants of Jehovah, You who stand in the house of Jehovah during the nights.  2 Raise your hands in holiness* And praise Jehovah.  3 May Jehovah, the Maker of heaven and earth, Bless you from Zion.

See Glossary.

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “and what will He add to you?”

Or “My soul has.”

Or “totter.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “your going out and your coming in.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “fortified walls.”

Or “Our soul has had more than enough.”

Or “our soul.”

Or “our soul.”

Or “Our soul is.”

Or “turn their hands to.”

Or “restore.”

Or “wadis in the south.”

Or “Children.”

Or “keep track of.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Lit., “be feared.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “My soul eagerly waits.”

Or “myself.” See Glossary.

Or “My soul is.”

Or “A grand tabernacle.”

Or “his grand tabernacle.”

Lit., “turn back the face of.”

Lit., “of the fruit of your womb.”

Lit., “horn.”

Or “diadem.”

Or possibly, “in the sanctuary.”

^ par. 21 (Luke 2:41-44) Now his parents were accustomed to go from year to year to Jerusalem for the festival of the Passover. 42 And when he was 12 years old, they went up according to the custom of the festival. 43 When the days of the festival were over and they were returning, the boy Jesus remained behind in Jerusalem, and his parents did not notice it. 44 Assuming that he was in the group traveling together, they went a day’s journey and then began to search for him among the relatives and acquaintances.

^ par. 22 (Luke 2:45, 46) But not finding him, they returned to Jerusalem and made a diligent search for him. 46 Well, after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the teachers and listening to them and asking them questions.

^ par. 23 (Luke 2:47, 48) But all those listening to him were in constant amazement at his understanding and his answers. 48 Now when his parents saw him, they were astounded, and his mother said to him: “Child, why did you treat us this way? Here your father and I have been frantically looking for you.”

^ par. 25 (Luke 2:49) But he said to them: “Why were you looking for me? Did you not know that I must be in the house of my Father?”

^ par. 27 (Eph. 6:4) And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ (Luke 2:51, 52) Then he went down with them and returned to Nazʹa·reth, and he continued subject* to them. Also, his mother carefully kept all these sayings in her heart. 52 And Jesus went on progressing in wisdom and in physical growth and in favor with God and men.

Or “remained obedient.”

^ par. 28 (Luke 2:51, 52) Then he went down with them and returned to Nazʹa·reth, and he continued subject* to them. Also, his mother carefully kept all these sayings in her heart. 52 And Jesus went on progressing in wisdom and in physical growth and in favor with God and men.

Or “remained obedient.”

^ par. 30 (Mark 6:3) This is the carpenter, the son of Mary and the brother of James, Joseph, Judas, and Simon, is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble because of him.

^ (Mark 6:3) This is the carpenter, the son of Mary and the brother of James, Joseph, Judas, and Simon, is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble because of him.

^ (John 2:1-5) And on the third day a marriage feast took place in Caʹna of Galʹi·lee, and the mother of Jesus was there. 2 Jesus and his disciples were also invited to the marriage feast. 3 When the wine ran short, the mother of Jesus said to him: “They have no wine.” 4 But Jesus said to her: “Woman, why is that of concern to me and to you?* My hour has not yet come.” 5 His mother said to those serving: “Do whatever he tells you.”

Lit., “What to me and to you, woman?” This is an idiom indicating objection. The use of “woman” does not denote disrespect.

^ (John 19:26, 27) So when Jesus saw his mother and the disciple whom he loved standing nearby, he said to his mother: “Woman, see! Your son!” 27 Next he said to the disciple: “See! Your mother!” And from that hour on, the disciple took her into his own home.

^ ***ia p. 170 He Protected, He Provided, He Persevered***

When Did Joseph Die?

We know that Joseph was alive when Jesus was 12 years old. At that age many Jewish youths began to learn their father’s trade and became apprentices at 15. Joseph evidently lived long enough to teach Jesus to be a carpenter. Was Joseph still living when Jesus began his ministry at about 30 years of age? That seems very doubtful. Jesus’ mother, brothers, and sisters are all mentioned as living at that time but not Joseph. Jesus was once even called “the son of Mary,” not the son of Joseph. ([Mark 6:3]) Mary is spoken of as acting and taking initiatives on her own, without consulting a husband. ([John 2:1-5]) That would have been unusual in Bible times unless she was a widow. Finally, as he was dying, Jesus entrusted the care of his mother to the apostle John. (John 19:26, 27) There would have been no need to do so if Joseph were still living. Likely, then, Joseph died when Jesus was still a relatively young man. As the eldest son, Jesus undoubtedly took over the carpentry business and cared for the family until his baptism.

^ (Mark 6:3) This is the carpenter, the son of Mary and the brother of James, Joseph, Judas, and Simon, is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble because of him.

^ (John 2:1-5) And on the third day a marriage feast took place in Caʹna of Galʹi·lee, and the mother of Jesus was there. 2 Jesus and his disciples were also invited to the marriage feast. 3 When the wine ran short, the mother of Jesus said to him: “They have no wine.” 4 But Jesus said to her: “Woman, why is that of concern to me and to you?* My hour has not yet come.” 5 His mother said to those serving: “Do whatever he tells you.”

Lit., “What to me and to you, woman?” This is an idiom indicating objection. The use of “woman” does not denote disrespect.

^ (John 19:26, 27) So when Jesus saw his mother and the disciple whom he loved standing nearby, he said to his mother: “Woman, see! Your son!” 27 Next he said to the disciple: “See! Your mother!” And from that hour on, the disciple took her into his own home.

^ ***ia chap. 19 He Protected, He Provided, He Persevered***

TO THINK ABOUT . . .

In what ways did Joseph act to protect his family?

How did Joseph provide for those who were his own?

What shows that Joseph persevered in his God-given assignment?

In what ways would you like to imitate the example of Joseph?

^ ***sn song 123 Shepherds—Gifts in Men***

Song 123

Shepherds—Gifts in Men

(Ephesians 4:8)

1. Help in our lives, Jehovah provides,

Shepherds to tend his flock.

By their example they serve as guides,

Showing us how to walk.

(CHORUS)

God gives us men who have earned our trust,

Men who are loyal and true.

They show concern for his precious flock;

Love them for all that they do.

2. Shepherds who love us care how we feel;

Gently they guide the way.

When we are hurt, they help us to heal,

Kind in the words they say.

(CHORUS)

God gives us men who have earned our trust,

Men who are loyal and true.

They show concern for his precious flock;

Love them for all that they do.

3. Godly advice and counsel they give,

That we may never stray.

Thus they assist us, God’s way to live,

Serving him ev’ry day.

(CHORUS)

God gives us men who have earned our trust,

Men who are loyal and true.

They show concern for his precious flock;

Love them for all that they do.

(See also Isa. 32:1, 2;[Jer. 3:15;] John 21:15-17;[Acts 20:28].)

^ (Eph. 4:8) For it says: “When he ascended on high he carried away captives; he gave gifts in men.”

^ (Isa. 32:1, 2) Look! A king will reign for righteousness, And princes will rule for justice.  2 And each one will be like a hiding place* from the wind, A place of concealment* from the rainstorm, Like streams of water in a waterless land, Like the shadow of a massive crag in a parched land.

Or “a shelter.”

Or “A refuge.”

^ (Jer. 3:15) And I will give you shepherds after my own heart, and they will feed you with knowledge and insight.

^ (John 21:15-17) When they had finished breakfast, Jesus said to Simon Peter: “Simon son of John, do you love me more than these?” He replied to him: “Yes, Lord, you know I have affection for you.” He said to him: “Feed my lambs.” 16 Again he said to him a second time: “Simon son of John, do you love me?” He replied: “Yes, Lord, you know I have affection for you.” He said to him: “Shepherd my little sheep.” 17 He said to him a third time: “Simon son of John, do you have affection for me?” Peter became grieved that he asked him the third time: “Do you have affection for me?” So he said to him: “Lord, you are aware of all things; you know that I have affection for you.” Jesus said to him: “Feed my little sheep.

^ (Acts 20:28) Pay attention to yourselves and to all the flock, among which the holy spirit has appointed you overseers, to shepherd the congregation of God, which he purchased with the blood of his own Son.

^ (Pss. 79:0-86:17) A melody of Aʹsaph. 79 O God, the nations have invaded your inheritance; They have defiled your holy temple; They have turned Jerusalem into a heap of ruins.  2 They have given the dead bodies of your servants as food to the birds of the heavens And the flesh of your loyal ones to the wild beasts of the earth.  3 They have poured out their blood like water around Jerusalem, And no one is left to bury them.  4 We have become an object of reproach to our neighbors; Those around us ridicule and jeer us.  5 How long, O Jehovah, will you be furious? Forever? How long will your indignation burn just like fire?  6 Pour out your wrath on the nations that do not know you And on the kingdoms that do not call on your name.  7 For they have devoured Jacob And have desolated his homeland.  8 Do not hold us accountable for the errors of our ancestors. Quickly show us your mercy, For we have been brought very low.  9 Help us, O God of our salvation, For the sake of your glorious name; Rescue us and forgive* our sins for the sake of your name. 10 Why should the nations say: “Where is their God?” Before our eyes may it become known among the nations That the shed blood of your servants has been avenged. 11 May you hear the sighing of the prisoner. Use your great power* to preserve* those sentenced to death.* 12 Repay our neighbors sevenfold For the taunts they have leveled at you, O Jehovah. 13 Then we, your people and the flock of your pasture, Will give thanks to you forever; And we will declare your praise from generation to generation.

To the director; set to “The Lilies.” A reminder. Of Aʹsaph. A melody. 80 O Shepherd of Israel, listen, You who are guiding Joseph just like a flock. You who sit enthroned above* the cherubs, Shine forth.*  2 Before Eʹphra·im and Benjamin and Ma·nasʹseh, Do stir up your mightiness; Come and save us.  3 O God, restore us; Let your face shine upon us, so that we may be saved.  4 Jehovah God of armies, how long will you be hostile toward* the prayer of your people?  5 You feed them tears as their bread, And you make them drink tears beyond measure.  6 You let our neighbors quarrel over us; Our enemies keep mocking us as they please.  7 O God of armies, restore us; Let your face shine upon us, so that we may be saved.  8 You made a vine depart from Egypt. You drove out the nations and planted it.  9 You cleared a space for it, And it took root and filled the land. 10 The mountains were covered by its shadow, And the cedars of God by its branches. 11 Its branches reached as far as the sea, And its shoots to the River.* 12 Why have you broken down the stone walls of the vineyard, So that all those passing by pluck its fruit? 13 The boars of the forest ravage it, And the wild animals of the field feed on it. 14 O God of armies, please return. Look down from heaven and see! Take care of this vine, 15 The stock* that your right hand has planted, And look upon the son whom* you made strong for yourself. 16 It is burned with fire, cut down. They perish at your rebuke.* 17 May your hand give support to the man at your right hand, To the son of man you have made strong for yourself. 18 Then we will not turn away from you. Preserve us alive, so that we may call on your name. 19 O Jehovah God of armies, restore us; Let your face shine upon us, so that we may be saved.

To the director; upon the Gitʹtith.* Of Aʹsaph. 81 Shout joyfully to God our strength. Shout in triumph to the God of Jacob.  2 Begin the music and take a tambourine, The melodious harp together with the stringed instrument.  3 Blow the horn on the new moon, On the full moon, for the day of our festival.  4 For it is a decree for Israel, A ruling of the God of Jacob.  5 He established it as a reminder for Joseph When He went out against the land of Egypt. I heard a voice* that I did not recognize:  6 “I lifted the burden from his shoulder; His hands were freed from the basket.  7 In your distress you called, and I rescued you; I answered you from the thundercloud.* I tested you at the waters of Merʹi·bah.* (Selah)  8 Hear, my people, and I will testify against you. O Israel, if you would only listen to me.  9 Among you, there will be no strange god, And you will not bow down to a foreign god. 10 I, Jehovah, am your God, The one who brought you out of the land of Egypt. Open your mouth wide, and I will fill it. 11 But my people did not listen to my voice; Israel would not submit to me. 12 So I let them follow their stubborn hearts; They did what they thought was right.* 13 If only my people would listen to me, If only Israel would walk in my ways! 14 Their enemies I would quickly subdue; I would turn my hand against their adversaries. 15 Those who hate Jehovah will cringe in his presence, And their outcome* will be forever. 16 But he will feed you* with the finest* wheat And satisfy you with honey from the rock.”

A melody of Aʹsaph. 82 God takes his place in the divine assembly;* In the middle of the gods* he judges:  2 “How long will you continue to judge with injustice And show partiality to the wicked? (Selah)  3 Defend* the lowly and the fatherless. Render justice to the helpless and destitute.  4 Rescue the lowly and the poor; Save them out of the hand of the wicked.”  5 They do not know, nor do they understand; They are walking about in darkness; All the foundations of the earth are being shaken.  6 “I have said, ‘You are gods,* All of you are sons of the Most High.  7 But you will die just as men do; And like any other prince you will fall!’”  8 Rise up, O God, and judge the earth, For all the nations belong to you.

A song. A melody of Aʹsaph. 83 O God, do not be silent; Do not keep quiet* or still, O Divine One.  2 For look! your enemies are in an uproar; Those who hate you act arrogantly.*  3 With cunning they secretly plot against your people; They conspire against your treasured ones.*  4 They say: “Come, let us annihilate them as a nation, So that the name of Israel may be remembered no more.”  5 They devise a unified strategy;* They have made an alliance* against you—  6 The tents of Eʹdom and the Ishʹma·el·ites, Moʹab and the Hagʹrites,  7 Geʹbal and Amʹmon and Amʹa·lek, Phi·lisʹti·a together with the inhabitants of Tyre.  8 As·syrʹi·a too has joined them; They give support to* the sons of Lot. (Selah)  9 Do to them as you did to Midʹi·an, As you did to Sisʹe·ra and Jaʹbin at the stream* of Kiʹshon. 10 They were annihilated at En-dor; They became manure for the ground. 11 Make their nobles like Oʹreb and Zeʹeb And their princes* like Zeʹbah and Zal·munʹna, 12 For they said: “Let us take possession of the land where God dwells.” 13 O my God, make them like a whirling thistle,* Like stubble blown about by the wind. 14 Like a fire that burns up the forest, Like a flame that scorches the mountains, 15 So may you pursue them with your tempest And terrify them with your windstorm. 16 Cover* their faces with dishonor, So that they may search for your name, O Jehovah. 17 May they be put to shame and be terrified forever; May they be disgraced and perish; 18 May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

For the director; upon the Gitʹtith.* Of the sons of Korʹah. A melody. 84 How lovely* your grand tabernacle is, O Jehovah of armies!  2 My whole being* yearns, Yes, I am faint with longing, For the courtyards of Jehovah. My heart and my flesh shout joyfully to the living God.  3 Even the bird finds a home there And the swallow a nest for herself, Where she cares for her young Near your grand altar, O Jehovah of armies, My King and my God!  4 Happy are those dwelling in your house! They continue to praise you. (Selah)  5 Happy are the men who find their strength in you, Whose hearts are set on the highways.  6 When they pass through the Baʹca Valley,* They make it into a place of springs; And the early rain clothes it* with blessings.  7 They will walk on from strength to strength; Each one appears before God in Zion.  8 O Jehovah God of armies, hear my prayer; Listen, O God of Jacob. (Selah)  9 Look, our shield and our God,* Look upon the face of your anointed one. 10 For a day in your courtyards is better than a thousand anywhere else! I choose to stand at the threshold of the house of my God Rather than to dwell in the tents of wickedness. 11 For Jehovah God is a sun and a shield; He gives favor and glory. Jehovah will not hold back anything good From those walking in integrity. 12 O Jehovah of armies, Happy is the man who trusts in you.

For the director. Of the sons of Korʹah. A melody. 85 You have shown favor, O Jehovah, to your land; You brought back those of Jacob who were taken captive.  2 You have pardoned the error of your people; You forgave* all their sin. (Selah)  3 You held back all your fury; You turned away from your hot anger.  4 Restore us,* O God of our salvation, And set aside your displeasure with us.  5 Will you be furious with us forever? Will you prolong your anger to generation after generation?  6 Will you not revive us again So that your people may rejoice in you?  7 Show your loyal love to us, O Jehovah, And grant us your salvation.  8 I will listen to what the true God Jehovah says, For he will speak peace to his people, to his loyal ones, But let them not return to overconfidence.  9 Surely his salvation is near to those who fear him, So that his glory may reside in our land. 10 Loyal love and faithfulness will meet together; Righteousness and peace will kiss each other. 11 Faithfulness will sprout from the earth, And righteousness will look down from the heavens. 12 Yes, Jehovah will give what is good,* And our land will yield its harvest. 13 Righteousness will walk before him And make a path for his footsteps.

A prayer of David. 86 Incline your ear,* O Jehovah, and answer me, For I am afflicted and poor.  2 Guard my life,* for I am loyal. Save your servant who is trusting in you, For you are my God.  3 Show me favor, O Jehovah, For I call to you all day long.  4 Make your servant* rejoice, For to you, O Jehovah, I turn.*  5 For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.  6 Listen, O Jehovah, to my prayer; And pay attention to my pleas for help.  7 I call on you in the day of my distress, For you will answer me.  8 There is none like you among the gods, O Jehovah, There are no works like yours.  9 All the nations that you made Will come and bow down before you, O Jehovah, And they will give glory to your name. 10 For you are great and do wondrous things; You are God, you alone. 11 Instruct me, O Jehovah, about your way. I will walk in your truth. Unify my heart* to fear your name. 12 I praise you, O Jehovah my God, with all my heart, And I will glorify your name forever, 13 For your loyal love toward me is great, And you have saved my life* from the depths of the Grave.* 14 O God, presumptuous men rise up against me; A band of ruthless men seek to take my life,* And they have no regard for you.* 15 But you, O Jehovah, are a God merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love and faithfulness.* 16 Turn to me and show me favor. Give your strength to your servant, And save the son of your slave girl. 17 Show me a sign* of your goodness, So that those who hate me may see it and be put to shame. For you, O Jehovah, are my helper and comforter.

Lit., “cover.”

Lit., “arm.”

Or possibly, “set free.”

Lit., “the sons of death.”

Or possibly, “between.”

Or “Reveal your radiance.”

Lit., “fume against.”

That is, the Euphrates.

Or “main stem of the vine.”

Or “branch that.”

Lit., “the rebuke of your face.”

See Glossary.

Or “language.”

Lit., “in the hidden place of thunder.”

Meaning “Quarreling.”

Lit., “They walked in their counsels.”

Lit., “time.”

Lit., “him,” that is, God’s people.

Lit., “the fat of.”

Or “in the assembly of the Divine One.”

Or “godlike ones.”

Or “Judge.”

Or “godlike ones.”

Or “keep speechless.”

Or “raise their heads.”

Lit., “concealed ones.”

Lit., “They consult with a heart together.”

Or “a covenant.”

Lit., “have become an arm to.”

Or “wadi.”

Or “leaders.”

Or “like tumbleweed.”

Lit., “Fill.”

See Glossary.

Or “deeply loved.”

Or “My soul.”

Or “the valley of baca bushes.”

Or possibly, “And the instructor enwraps himself.”

Or possibly, “Look at our shield, O God.”

Lit., “covered.”

Or “Gather us back.”

Or “prosperity.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or “soul.”

Or “the soul of your servant.”

Or “I raise my soul.”

Or “Give me an undivided heart.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “seek my soul.”

Or “have not set you in front of themselves.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “and truth.”

Or “evidence.”

^ (Pss. 85:8-86:17) I will listen to what the true God Jehovah says, For he will speak peace to his people, to his loyal ones, But let them not return to overconfidence.  9 Surely his salvation is near to those who fear him, So that his glory may reside in our land. 10 Loyal love and faithfulness will meet together; Righteousness and peace will kiss each other. 11 Faithfulness will sprout from the earth, And righteousness will look down from the heavens. 12 Yes, Jehovah will give what is good,* And our land will yield its harvest. 13 Righteousness will walk before him And make a path for his footsteps.

A prayer of David. 86 Incline your ear,* O Jehovah, and answer me, For I am afflicted and poor.  2 Guard my life,* for I am loyal. Save your servant who is trusting in you, For you are my God.  3 Show me favor, O Jehovah, For I call to you all day long.  4 Make your servant* rejoice, For to you, O Jehovah, I turn.*  5 For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.  6 Listen, O Jehovah, to my prayer; And pay attention to my pleas for help.  7 I call on you in the day of my distress, For you will answer me.  8 There is none like you among the gods, O Jehovah, There are no works like yours.  9 All the nations that you made Will come and bow down before you, O Jehovah, And they will give glory to your name. 10 For you are great and do wondrous things; You are God, you alone. 11 Instruct me, O Jehovah, about your way. I will walk in your truth. Unify my heart* to fear your name. 12 I praise you, O Jehovah my God, with all my heart, And I will glorify your name forever, 13 For your loyal love toward me is great, And you have saved my life* from the depths of the Grave.* 14 O God, presumptuous men rise up against me; A band of ruthless men seek to take my life,* And they have no regard for you.* 15 But you, O Jehovah, are a God merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love and faithfulness.* 16 Turn to me and show me favor. Give your strength to your servant, And save the son of your slave girl. 17 Show me a sign* of your goodness, So that those who hate me may see it and be put to shame. For you, O Jehovah, are my helper and comforter.

Or “prosperity.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or “soul.”

Or “the soul of your servant.”

Or “I raise my soul.”

Or “Give me an undivided heart.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “seek my soul.”

Or “have not set you in front of themselves.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “and truth.”

Or “evidence.”

^ ***snnw song 138 Jehovah Is Your Name***

Song 138

Jehovah Is Your Name

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

([Psalm 83:18])

The living and true God—

The God of all creation

In ev’ry generation—

Jehovah is your name.

We’re honored and we’re proud

To be your congregation.

In ev’ry tribe and nation,

Your glory we proclaim.

(CHORUS)

Jehovah, Jehovah,

There is no God like you.

There’s no other in the heavens

Or on the earth below.

You alone are God Almighty,

And this all men must know.

Jehovah, Jehovah,

We have no other God but you.

You cause us to become

Whatever you desire,

To do as you require—

Jehovah is your name.

And Witnesses for you

Is what you’ve kindly named us.

We’re honored you have claimed us—

A people for your name.

(CHORUS)

Jehovah, Jehovah,

There is no God like you.

There’s no other in the heavens

Or on the earth below.

You alone are God Almighty,

And this all men must know.

Jehovah, Jehovah,

We have no other God but you.

(See also 2 Chron. 6:14;[Ps. 72:19;][Isa. 42:8].)

^ (Ps. 83:18) May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

^ (2 Chron. 6:14) and he said: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, there is no God like you in the heavens or on the earth, keeping the covenant and showing loyal love to your servants who are walking before you with all their heart.

^ (Ps. 72:19) May his glorious name be praised forever, And may his glory fill the whole earth. Amen and Amen.

^ (Isa. 42:8) I am Jehovah. That is my name; I give my glory to no one else,* Nor my praise to graven images.

Or “I do not share my glory with anyone else.”

^ ***w08 10/15 p. 13 Jehovah’s Answer to a Heartfelt Prayer***

7 What was the psalmist’s foremost concern? Of course, he must have been very worried about his own personal safety and that of his family. Yet, the subject of his prayer was the reproach being brought on Jehovah’s name and the threats against the nation that bore that name. May we all keep a similar, balanced viewpoint as we endure the difficult final days of this old world.—Read Matthew 6:9, 10.

8. What was the objective of the nations in conspiring against Israel?

8 The psalmist quotes Israel’s enemies as saying: “Come and let us efface them from being a nation, that the name of Israel may be remembered no more.” ([Ps. 83:4]) What hatred those nations had for God’s chosen people! But they had another motive for their conspiracy. They coveted Israel’s land and boasted: “Let us take possession of the abiding places of God for ourselves.” ([Ps. 83:12]) Has something similar been true in our day? Yes!

^ par. 7 (Matt. 6:9, 10) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.* 10 Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

Or “be held sacred; be treated as holy.”

^ par. 8 (Ps. 83:4) They say: “Come, let us annihilate them as a nation, So that the name of Israel may be remembered no more.”

^ par. 8 (Ps. 83:12) For they said: “Let us take possession of the land where God dwells.”

^ ***w08 10/15 p. 15 Jehovah’s Answer to a Heartfelt Prayer***

Pray for Jehovah’s Vindication

16. How have the faces of opposers been ‘filled with dishonor’ today?

16 Throughout these “last days,” Jehovah has thwarted all efforts to eliminate his people. ([2 Tim. 3:1]) As a result, opposers have been shamed. [Psalm 83:16] foreshadowed this when it said: “Fill their faces with dishonor, that people may search for your name, O Jehovah.” In country after country, opponents have failed miserably in their effort to silence Jehovah’s Witnesses. In those lands, the steadfastness and endurance of worshippers of the one true God have served as a witness to righthearted ones, and many have ‘searched for Jehovah’s name.’ In a number of lands where Jehovah’s Witnesses were once viciously persecuted, there are now tens of thousands, even hundreds of thousands, of happy praisers of Jehovah. What a triumph for Jehovah! And how embarrassing for his enemies!—Read Jeremiah 1:19.

^ par. 16 (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ par. 16 (Ps. 83:16) Cover* their faces with dishonor, So that they may search for your name, O Jehovah.

Lit., “Fill.”

^ par. 16 (Jer. 1:19) And they will certainly fight against you, But they will not prevail against you,* For ‘I am with you,’ declares Jehovah, ‘to save you.’”

Or “defeat you.”

^ ***w11 5/15 p. 16 Who Is the Most Important Person in Your Life?***

1, 2. With regard to our personal salvation, why is it not enough just to know Jehovah’s name?

PERHAPS the first time you saw Jehovah’s name was when it was shown to you at [Psalm 83:18]. You may have been surprised to read those words: “That people may know that you, whose name is Jehovah, you alone are the Most High over all the earth.” Since then, you no doubt have used this same scripture to help others come to know our loving God, Jehovah.—Rom. 10:12, 13.

2 Although it is important for people to know Jehovah’s name, such knowledge in itself is not enough. Notice how the psalmist highlights yet another truth essential to our salvation when he says: “You alone are the Most High over all the earth.” Yes, Jehovah is the most important Person in the whole universe. As the Creator of all things, he has the right to expect full submission from all his creatures. ([Rev. 4:11]) For good reason, then, we need to ask ourselves, ‘Who is the most important person in my life?’ It is vital that we carefully analyze our answer to that question!

^ par. 1 (Ps. 83:18) May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

^ par. 1 (Rom. 10:12, 13) For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek. There is the same Lord over all, who is rich* toward all those calling on him. 13 For “everyone who calls on the name of Jehovah* will be saved.”

Or “generous.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 2 (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ ***w08 10/15 pp. 15-16 Jehovah’s Answer to a Heartfelt Prayer***

17. What critical situation faces mankind, and what words will we soon remember?

17 We know, of course, that the battle is not over. And we continue to preach the good news—even to opposers. ([Matt. 24:14,][21]) However, the opportunity now open to such opposers to repent and gain salvation will soon come to an end. The sanctification of Jehovah’s name is far more important than human salvation. (Read Ezekiel 38:23.) When the nations combine in the foretold earth-wide effort to destroy God’s people, we will remember these words of the psalmist’s prayer: “O may they be ashamed and be disturbed for all times, and may they become abashed and perish.”—[Ps. 83:17].

18, 19. (a) What awaits determined opposers of Jehovah’s sovereignty? (b) How does the approaching final vindication of Jehovah’s sovereignty affect you?

18 A humiliating end awaits determined opposers of Jehovah’s sovereignty. God’s Word reveals that those who “do not obey the good news”—and for this reason are executed at Armageddon—will suffer “everlasting destruction.” (2 Thess. 1:7-9) Their destruction and the survival of those who worship Jehovah in truth will be convincing evidence that Jehovah is the only true God. In the new world, that great victory will not be forgotten. Those who come back in the “resurrection of . . . the righteous and the unrighteous” will learn of Jehovah’s great act. ([Acts 24:15]) In the new world, they will see convincing evidence of the wisdom of living under Jehovah’s sovereignty. And meek ones among them will quickly be convinced that Jehovah is the only true God.

^ par. 17 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ par. 17 (Matt. 24:21) for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again.

^ par. 17 (Ezek. 38:23) And I will certainly magnify myself and sanctify myself and make myself known before the eyes of many nations; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

^ par. 17 (Ps. 83:17) May they be put to shame and be terrified forever; May they be disgraced and perish;

^ par. 18 (2 Thess. 1:7-9) But you who suffer tribulation will be given relief along with us at the revelation of the Lord Jesus from heaven with his powerful angels 8 in a flaming fire, as he brings vengeance on those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus. 9 These very ones will undergo the judicial punishment of everlasting destruction from before the Lord and from the glory of his strength,

^ par. 18 (Acts 24:15) And I have hope toward God, which hope these men also look forward to, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous.

^ ***w06 7/15 p. 12 par. 5 Highlights From Books Three and Four of Psalms***

79:9. Jehovah listens to our prayers, especially when they are concerning the sanctification of his name.

^ par. 5 (Ps. 79:9) Help us, O God of our salvation, For the sake of your glorious name; Rescue us and forgive* our sins for the sake of your name.

Lit., “cover.”

^ ***w06 7/15 p. 12 par. 9 Highlights From Books Three and Four of Psalms***

86:5. How grateful we can be that Jehovah is “ready to forgive”! He is on the lookout for any evidence that would provide a basis for him to show mercy to a repentant wrongdoer.

^ par. 9 (Ps. 86:5) For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.

^ ***fg lesson 7***

The Kingdom of God is a heavenly government. It will replace all other governments and will cause God’s will to be done in heaven and on earth. The news about God’s Kingdom is good. Soon God’s Kingdom will satisfy man’s need for good government. It will unite everyone living on earth.—Read Daniel 2:44; Matthew 6:9, 10; 24:14.

^ par. 1 (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ par. 1 (Matt. 6:9, 10) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.* 10 Let your Kingdom come. Let your will take place, as in heaven, also on earth.

Or “be held sacred; be treated as holy.”

^ par. 1 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ ***fg lesson 7***

God’s Son is the ideal King because he is kind and he is firm for what is right. ([John 1:14]) Also, he is powerful enough to help people because he will rule over the earth from heaven. After he was resurrected, he ascended to heaven and sat down to wait at Jehovah’s right hand. (Hebrews 10:12, 13) Finally, God gave him power to begin ruling.—Read Daniel 7:13, 14.

^ par. 3 (John 1:14) So the Word became flesh and resided among us, and we had a view of his glory, a glory such as belongs to an only-begotten son from a father; and he was full of divine favor* and truth.

Or “of undeserved kindness.”

^ par. 3 (Heb. 10:12, 13) But this man offered one sacrifice for sins for all time and sat down at the right hand of God, 13 from then on waiting until his enemies should be placed as a stool for his feet.

^ par. 3 (Dan. 7:13, 14) “I kept watching in the visions of the night, and look! with the clouds of the heavens, someone like a son of man was coming; and he gained access to the Ancient of Days, and they brought him up close before that One. 14 And to him there were given rulership, honor, and a kingdom, that the peoples, nations, and language groups should all serve him. His rulership is an everlasting rulership that will not pass away, and his kingdom will not be destroyed.

^ ***fg lesson 7***

By means of a global preaching work, God’s Kingdom is already uniting a great crowd of people from all nations. Millions of meek people are becoming subjects of Jesus. God’s Kingdom will protect them when it destroys the present wicked system of things on earth. So all who want to benefit from God’s Kingdom should learn to be obedient subjects of Jesus.—Read Revelation 7:9, 14, 16, 17.

During a period of 1,000 years, the Kingdom will accomplish God’s original purpose for mankind. The earth will become a global paradise. Finally, Jesus will hand the Kingdom back to his Father. (1 Corinthians 15:24-26) Do you know someone whom you would like to tell about God’s Kingdom?—Read Psalm 37:10, 11, 29.

^ par. 7 (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ par. 7 (Rev. 7:14) So right away I said to him: “My lord, you are the one who knows.” And he said to me: “These are the ones who come out of the great tribulation, and they have washed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.

^ par. 7 (Rev. 7:16, 17) They will hunger no more nor thirst anymore, neither will the sun beat down on them nor any scorching heat, 17 because the Lamb, who is in the midst* of the throne, will shepherd them and will guide them to springs* of waters of life. And God will wipe out every tear from their eyes.”

Or “at the center.”

Or “fountains.”

^ par. 8 (1 Cor. 15:24-26) Next, the end, when he hands over the Kingdom to his God and Father, when he has brought to nothing all government and all authority and power. 25 For he must rule as king until God has put all enemies under his feet. 26 And the last enemy, death, is to be brought to nothing.

^ par. 8 (Ps. 37:10, 11) Just a little while longer, and the wicked will be no more; You will look at where they were, And they will not be there. 11 But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

^ par. 8 (Ps. 37:29) The righteous will possess the earth, And they will live forever on it.

^ ***sn song 111 He Will Call***

Song 111

He Will Call

([Job 14:13-15])

1. Life, like a mist, appears for just a day,

Then disappears tomorrow.

All that we are can quickly fade away,

Replaced with tears and sorrow.

If a man should die, can he live again?

Hear the promise God has made:

(CHORUS)

He will call; The dead will answer.

They shall live at his command.

For he will have a longing

For the work of his own hand.

So have faith, and do not wonder,

For our God can make us stand.

And we shall live forever,

As the work of his own hand.

2. Friends of our God, though they may pass away,

Will never be forsaken.

All those asleep who in God’s mem’ry stay,

From death he will awaken.

Then we’ll come to see all that life can be:

Paradise eternally.

(CHORUS)

He will call; The dead will answer.

They shall live at his command.

For he will have a longing

For the work of his own hand.

So have faith, and do not wonder,

For our God can make us stand.

And we shall live forever,

As the work of his own hand.

(See also [John 6:40;][11:11,][43;][Jas. 4:14].)

^ (Job 14:13-15) O that in the Grave* you would conceal me, That you would hide me until your anger passes by, That you would set a time limit for me and remember me! 14 If a man dies, can he live again? I will wait all the days of my compulsory service Until my relief comes. 15 You will call, and I will answer you. You will long* for the work of your hands.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “yearn.”

^ (John 6:40) For this is the will of my Father, that everyone who recognizes the Son and exercises faith in him should have everlasting life, and I will resurrect him on the last day.”

^ (John 11:11) After he said these things, he added: “Lazʹa·rus our friend has fallen asleep, but I am traveling there to awaken him.”

^ (John 11:43) When he had said these things, he cried out with a loud voice: “Lazʹa·rus, come out!”

^ (Jas. 4:14) whereas you do not know what your life will be like tomorrow. For you are a mist that appears for a little while and then disappears.

^ ***fg pp. 4-5***

LESSON 2

Who Is God?

1. Why should we worship God?

The true God is the Creator of all things. He had no beginning and will never have an end. ([Psalm 90:2]) He is the Source of the good news found in the Bible. (1 Timothy 1:11) Since God gave us life, we should worship only him.—Read Revelation 4:11.

2. What is God like?

No human has ever seen God because he is a Spirit, which means that he is a higher form of life than the physical creatures who live on earth. ([John 1:18;][4:24]) Nevertheless, we can discern God’s personality from the things he has made. For instance, the variety of fruits and flowers tells us of his love and wisdom. The size of the universe tells us of his power.—Read Romans 1:20.

We can learn even more about God’s personality by reading the Bible. For example, it tells us what God likes and what he does not like, how he treats people, and how he reacts in different situations.—Read Psalm 103:7-10.

3. Does God have a name?

Jesus said: “Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.” ([Matthew 6:9]) Although God has many titles, he has only one name. In each language, it is pronounced differently. In English it is usually pronounced “Jehovah.” But some people pronounce it “Yahweh.”—Read Psalm 83:18.

God’s name has been taken out of many Bibles and replaced with the titles Lord or God. But when the Bible was written, it contained God’s name some 7,000 times. Jesus made God’s name known when he taught people about God.—Read John 17:26.

4. Does Jehovah care about us?

Does widespread suffering mean that Jehovah is a God who does not care about us? Some people claim that he makes us suffer to test us, but this is not true.—Read James 1:13.

God has granted man the dignity of free will. Do we not appreciate our freedom to choose to serve God? ([Joshua 24:15]) But many choose to do bad things to others, so suffering abounds. It saddens Jehovah to see such injustice.—Read Genesis 6:5, 6.

Jehovah is a God who cares about us. He wants us to enjoy life. Soon he will eliminate suffering and those who cause it. Meanwhile, he has good reason to allow suffering for a limited time. In Lesson 8, we will learn what that reason is.—Read 2 Peter 2:9; 3:7, 13.

5. How can we draw closer to God?

Jehovah invites us to draw close to him by speaking to him in prayer. He is interested in us individually. ([Psalm 65:2;][145:18]) He is willing to forgive. He recognizes our efforts to please him, even if we sometimes fail. So despite our imperfection, we really can enjoy a close relationship with God.—Read Psalm 103:12-14; James 4:8.

Since Jehovah has given us life, we should love him more than we love anyone else. ([Mark 12:30]) As you express your love for God by learning more about him and doing as he asks, you will draw ever closer to him.—Read 1 Timothy 2:4; 1 John 5:3.

^ par. 1 (Ps. 90:2) Before the mountains were born Or you brought forth* the earth and the productive land, From everlasting to everlasting,* you are God.

Or “brought forth as with labor pains.”

Or “From eternity to eternity.”

^ par. 1 (1 Tim. 1:11) according to the glorious good news of the happy God, with which I was entrusted.

^ par. 1 (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 2 (John 1:18) No man has seen God at any time; the only-begotten god who is at the Father’s side* is the one who has explained Him.

Or “in the bosom position with the Father.” This refers to a position of special favor.

^ par. 2 (John 4:24) God is a Spirit, and those worshipping him must worship with spirit and truth.”

^ par. 2 (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 103:7-10) He made known his ways to Moses, His deeds to the sons of Israel.  8 Jehovah is merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love.*  9 He will not always find fault, Nor will he stay resentful forever. 10 He has not dealt with us according to our sins, Nor has he repaid us what our errors deserve.

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

^ par. 4 (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.*

Or “be held sacred; be treated as holy.”

^ par. 4 (Ps. 83:18) May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

^ par. 5 (John 17:26) I have made your name known to them and will make it known, so that the love with which you loved me may be in them and I in union with them.”

^ par. 6 (Jas. 1:13) When under trial, let no one say: “I am being tried by God.” For with evil things God cannot be tried, nor does he himself try anyone.

^ par. 7 (Josh. 24:15) Now if it seems bad to you to serve Jehovah, choose for yourselves today whom you will serve, whether the gods that your forefathers served on the other side of the River* or the gods of the Amʹor·ites in whose land you are dwelling. But as for me and my household, we will serve Jehovah.”

That is, the Euphrates.

^ par. 7 (Gen. 6:5, 6) Consequently, Jehovah saw that man’s wickedness was great on the earth and that every inclination of the thoughts of his heart was only bad all the time. 6 Jehovah regretted* that he had made men on the earth, and his heart was saddened.*

Or “was grieved.”

Or “and he felt hurt at his heart.”

^ par. 8 (2 Pet. 2:9) So, then, Jehovah* knows how to rescue people of godly devotion out of trial, but to reserve unrighteous people to be destroyed* on the day of judgment,

See App. A5.

Lit., “cut off.”

^ par. 8 (2 Pet. 3:7) But by the same word the heavens and the earth that now exist are reserved for fire and are being kept until the day of judgment and of destruction of the ungodly people.

^ par. 8 (2 Pet. 3:13) But there are new heavens and a new earth that we are awaiting according to his promise, and in these righteousness is to dwell.

^ par. 9 (Ps. 65:2) O Hearer of prayer, to you people of all sorts* will come.

Lit., “all flesh.”

^ par. 9 (Ps. 145:18) Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.*

Or “in sincerity.”

^ par. 9 (Ps. 103:12-14) As far off as the sunrise is from the sunset, So far off from us he has put our transgressions. 13 As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him. 14 For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ par. 9 (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ par. 10 (Mark 12:30) and you must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

^ par. 10 (1 Tim. 2:4) whose will is that all sorts of people should be saved and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.

^ par. 10 (1 John 5:3) For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome,

^ ***ia pp. 176-179 “I Have Believed”***

A Beloved Brother Lost—And Restored

14. Why can we be sure that Martha set a good example in accepting correction?

14 Did Martha accept Jesus’ gentle reproof and learn from it? We need not wonder. The apostle John, in introducing a thrilling account about Martha’s brother, reminds us: “Now Jesus loved Martha and her sister and Lazarus.” ([John 11:5]) Months had passed since Jesus’ visit to Bethany described above. Clearly, Martha had not indulged in sulking; she was not nursing a grudge against Jesus for his loving counsel. She had taken it to heart. In this matter too, she set an excellent example of faith for us, for who of us does not need a little correction at times?

15, 16. (a) How did Martha surely respond when her brother took ill? (b) Why were Martha’s and Mary’s hopes dashed?

15 When her brother took ill, Martha surely busied herself with his care. She did everything in her power to soothe his discomfort and help him get better. Nonetheless, Lazarus sank still deeper into his illness. Hour after hour, his sisters stayed by his side to care for him. How often Martha must have gazed into her brother’s haggard face, remembering their many years together and the joys and sorrows they had shared!

16 When it looked as if Lazarus was beyond their help, Martha and Mary sent a message to Jesus. He was preaching some two days’ journey away. Their message was simple: “Lord, see! the one for whom you have affection is sick.” ([John 11:1,][3]) They knew that Jesus loved their brother, and they had faith that he would do whatever he could to help his friend. Did they cling to the hope that Jesus might arrive before it was too late? If so, their hopes were dashed. Lazarus died.

17. What puzzled Martha, and how did she react when she heard that Jesus was nearing the town?

17 Together, Martha and Mary mourned their brother, taking care of the preparations for his burial and receiving the many guests from Bethany and its environs. Still, no news of Jesus. Martha may have grown more puzzled as the time passed. Finally, four days after Lazarus’ death, Martha heard that Jesus was nearing the town. Ever the woman of action, even in this grim hour, Martha got up and, without telling Mary, rushed out to meet Jesus.—Read John 11:18-20.

18, 19. Martha expressed what hope, and why was her faith remarkable?

18 When Martha caught sight of her Master, she put into words the thought that had been tormenting her and Mary for days: “Lord, if you had been here my brother would not have died.” But hope and faith were not dead in Martha. She added: “And yet at present I know that as many things as you ask God for, God will give you.” Jesus immediately said something to strengthen her faith: “Your brother will rise.”—John 11:21-23.

19 Martha thought that Jesus was talking about the future resurrection, so she replied: “I know he will rise in the resurrection on the last day.” ([John 11:24]) Her faith in that teaching was remarkable. Some Jewish religious leaders, called Sadducees, denied that there would be a resurrection, though it was a clear teaching in the inspired Scriptures. ([Dan. 12:13;][Mark 12:18]) Martha knew, however, that Jesus taught the resurrection hope and had even performed resurrections—although not of anyone who had been dead as long as Lazarus had. She did not know what lay ahead.

20. Explain the meaning of Jesus’ unforgettable statement recorded at John 11:25-27 and of Martha’s reply.

20 Jesus then made an unforgettable statement: “I am the resurrection and the life.” Indeed, Jehovah God has given his Son the authority to perform resurrections on a global scale in the future. Jesus asked Martha: “Do you believe this?” Then she gave the answer discussed at the outset of this chapter. She had faith that Jesus was the Christ, or Messiah, that he was the Son of Jehovah God, and that he was the one whom the prophets had foretold would come into the world.—John 5:28, 29; read John 11:25-27.

21, 22. (a) How did Jesus reveal his feelings for those who mourn? (b) Describe the resurrection of Lazarus.

21 Do Jehovah God and his Son, Jesus Christ, value faith like that of Martha? The events that next unfolded before Martha’s eyes provide the clearest of answers. She hurried to get her sister. Thereafter, she saw that Jesus was deeply moved as he talked to Mary and the many mourners with her. She saw the tears come to his eyes as he freely showed his deep grief over the pain that death causes. She heard Jesus order that the stone be rolled away from her brother’s tomb.—John 11:28-39.

22 Ever practical, Martha objected that the body would smell by now, four days after death. Jesus reminded her: “Did I not tell you that if you would believe you would see the glory of God?” She did believe, and she did see the glory of Jehovah God. Right then and there, he empowered his Son to bring Lazarus back to life! Think of the moments that must have been etched in Martha’s memory to the end of her days: Jesus’ commanding call, “Lazarus, come on out!”; the faint noise from the cave where Lazarus was entombed as the man rose and, still bound in the bandages used to prepare the body, inched his way to the door of the cave; Jesus’ command to “loose him and let him go”; and, to be sure, the ecstatic embrace as Martha and Mary flew into their brother’s arms. (Read John 11:40-44.) The burden on Martha’s heart was lifted!

23. What do Jehovah and Jesus want to do for you, and what do you need to do?

23 This account shows that the resurrection of the dead is not mere wishful thinking; it is a heartwarming Bible teaching and a proven historical reality. (Job 14:14, 15) Jehovah and his Son love to reward faith, as they did in the case of Martha, Mary, and Lazarus. They have such rewards in store for you too if you build strong faith.

“Martha Was Ministering”

24. The Bible record gives us what last glimpse of Martha?

24 The Bible record mentions Martha just one more time. It was at the outset of the final week of Jesus’ life on earth. Knowing well what hardships lay ahead of him, Jesus again chose that haven at Bethany as his residence. From there he would walk the two miles (3 km) to Jerusalem. Jesus and Lazarus were dining at the home of Simon the leper, and there we get this last glimpse of our subject: “Martha was ministering.”—[John 12:2].

25. Why are congregations today blessed to have women like Martha?

25 How typical of that industrious woman! When we first come upon her in the Bible, she is working; when we leave her, she is still working, doing her best to care for the needs of those around her. Congregations of Christ’s followers today are blessed to have women like Martha—stouthearted and generous, always putting their faith into action by giving of themselves. Did Martha keep doing just that? It seems likely. If so, she acted wisely, for she had yet to meet her share of obstacles.

26. What did Martha’s faith help her to do?

26 Within days, Martha had to endure the terrible death of her beloved Master, Jesus. Further, the same murderous hypocrites who killed him were determined to kill Lazarus as well, since his resurrection was boosting the faith of so many. (Read John 12:9-11.) And, of course, death did eventually sever the loving bonds that joined Martha to her siblings. We do not know how or when that happened, but we may be fairly sure of this: Martha’s precious faith helped her endure to the end. That is why Christians today do well to imitate the faith of Martha.

^ par. 14 (John 11:5) Now Jesus loved Martha and her sister and Lazʹa·rus.

^ par. 16 (John 11:1) Now a man named Lazʹa·rus was sick; he was from Bethʹa·ny, the village of Mary and her sister Martha.

^ par. 16 (John 11:3) So his sisters sent a message to him, saying: “Lord, see! the one you have affection for is sick.”

^ par. 17 (John 11:18-20) Now Bethʹa·ny was near Jerusalem, about two miles* away. 19 And many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary to console them concerning their brother. 20 When Martha heard that Jesus was coming, she went to meet him; but Mary kept sitting at home.

About three km. Lit., “about 15 stadia.” See App. B14.

^ par. 18 (John 11:21-23) Martha then said to Jesus: “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died. 22 Yet even now I know that whatever you ask God for, God will give you.” 23 Jesus said to her: “Your brother will rise.”

^ par. 19 (John 11:24) Martha said to him: “I know he will rise in the resurrection on the last day.”

^ par. 19 (Dan. 12:13) “But as for you, go on to the end. You will rest, but you will stand up for your lot* at the end of the days.”

Or “in your allotted place.”

^ par. 19 (Mark 12:18) Now the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, came and asked him:

^ (John 11:25-27) Jesus said to her: “I am the resurrection and the life. The one who exercises faith in me, even though he dies, will come to life; 26 and everyone who is living and exercises faith in me will never die at all. Do you believe this?” 27 She said to him: “Yes, Lord, I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of God, the one coming into the world.”

^ par. 20 (John 5:28, 29) Do not be amazed at this, for the hour is coming in which all those in the memorial tombs will hear his voice 29 and come out, those who did good things to a resurrection of life, and those who practiced vile things to a resurrection of judgment.

^ par. 20 (John 11:25-27) Jesus said to her: “I am the resurrection and the life. The one who exercises faith in me, even though he dies, will come to life; 26 and everyone who is living and exercises faith in me will never die at all. Do you believe this?” 27 She said to him: “Yes, Lord, I have believed that you are the Christ, the Son of God, the one coming into the world.”

^ par. 21 (John 11:28-39) When she had said this, she went off and called Mary her sister, saying privately: “The Teacher is here and is calling you.” 29 On hearing this, she got up quickly and went to him. 30 Jesus had not yet come into the village, but he was still in the place where Martha had met him. 31 When the Jews who were with Mary in the house consoling her saw her get up quickly and go out, they followed her, supposing that she was going to the tomb* to weep there. 32 When Mary arrived where Jesus was and caught sight of him, she fell at his feet and said to him: “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.” 33 When Jesus saw her weeping and the Jews who had come with her weeping, he groaned within himself* and became troubled. 34 He said: “Where have you laid him?” They said to him: “Lord, come and see.” 35 Jesus gave way to tears. 36 At that the Jews began to say: “See, what affection he had for him!” 37 But some of them said: “Could not this man who opened the eyes of the blind man prevent this one from dying?” 38 Then Jesus, after groaning again within himself, came to the tomb.* It was, in fact, a cave, and a stone was lying against it. 39 Jesus said: “Take the stone away.” Martha, the sister of the deceased, said to him: “Lord, by now he must smell, for it has been four days.”

Or “memorial tomb.”

Lit., “in the spirit.”

Or “memorial tomb.”

^ par. 22 (John 11:40-44) Jesus said to her: “Did I not tell you that if you would believe you would see the glory of God?” 41 So they took the stone away. Then Jesus raised his eyes heavenward and said: “Father, I thank you that you have heard me. 42 True, I knew that you always hear me; but I spoke on account of the crowd standing around, so that they may believe that you sent me.” 43 When he had said these things, he cried out with a loud voice: “Lazʹa·rus, come out!” 44 The man who had been dead came out with his feet and hands bound with wrappings, and his face was wrapped with a cloth. Jesus said to them: “Free him and let him go.”

^ par. 23 (Job 14:14, 15) If a man dies, can he live again? I will wait all the days of my compulsory service Until my relief comes. 15 You will call, and I will answer you. You will long* for the work of your hands.

Or “yearn.”

^ par. 24 (John 12:2) So they spread an evening meal for him there, and Martha was serving them, but Lazʹa·rus was one of those dining* with him.

Or “reclining at the table.”

^ par. 26 (John 12:9-11) Meanwhile, a large crowd of Jews got to know that he was there, and they came not only because of Jesus but also to see Lazʹa·rus, whom he had raised up from the dead. 10 The chief priests now conspired to kill Lazʹa·rus also, 11 since it was because of him that many of the Jews were going there and putting faith in Jesus.

^ ***ia chap. 20 “I Have Believed”***

TO THINK ABOUT . . .

What can we learn from the counsel Jesus gave Martha?

In what ways did Martha display a giving, industrious spirit?

How did Martha show remarkable faith?

In what ways would you like to imitate the faith of Martha?

^ ***snnw song 143 Light in a Darkened World***

Song 143

Light in a Darkened World

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(2 Corinthians 4:6)

In these days, dark and lawless days,

Shines a light we can see.

Like the dawn of another day

That will soon come to be.

(CHORUS)

Shining through the darkness,

Ours is a message so bright.

It offers hope and light—

Sparkling like the daylight,

Bringing tomorrow in sight—

So ends the night.

Those who sleep need awakening

As the time ebbs away.

We give hope and encouragement.

For their future we’ll pray.

(CHORUS)

Shining through the darkness,

Ours is a message so bright.

It offers hope and light—

Sparkling like the daylight,

Bringing tomorrow in sight—

So ends the night.

(See also [John 3:19;][8:12;] Rom. 13:11, 12;[1 Pet. 2:9].)

^ (2 Cor. 4:6) For God is the one who said: “Let the light shine out of darkness,” and he has shone on our hearts to illuminate them with the glorious knowledge of God by the face of Christ.

^ (John 3:19) Now this is the basis for judgment: that the light has come into the world, but men have loved the darkness rather than the light, for their works were wicked.

^ (John 8:12) Then Jesus spoke again to them, saying: “I am the light of the world. Whoever follows me will by no means walk in darkness, but will possess the light of life.”

^ (Rom. 13:11, 12) And do this because you know the season, that it is already the hour for you to awake from sleep, for now our salvation is nearer than at the time when we became believers. 12 The night is well along; the day has drawn near. Let us therefore throw off the works belonging to darkness and let us put on the weapons of the light.

^ (1 Pet. 2:9) But you are “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for special possession, that you should declare abroad the excellencies”* of the One who called you out of darkness into his wonderful light.

Lit., “the virtues,” that is, his praiseworthy qualities and deeds.

^ (Pss. 79:0-86:17) A melody of Aʹsaph. 79 O God, the nations have invaded your inheritance; They have defiled your holy temple; They have turned Jerusalem into a heap of ruins.  2 They have given the dead bodies of your servants as food to the birds of the heavens And the flesh of your loyal ones to the wild beasts of the earth.  3 They have poured out their blood like water around Jerusalem, And no one is left to bury them.  4 We have become an object of reproach to our neighbors; Those around us ridicule and jeer us.  5 How long, O Jehovah, will you be furious? Forever? How long will your indignation burn just like fire?  6 Pour out your wrath on the nations that do not know you And on the kingdoms that do not call on your name.  7 For they have devoured Jacob And have desolated his homeland.  8 Do not hold us accountable for the errors of our ancestors. Quickly show us your mercy, For we have been brought very low.  9 Help us, O God of our salvation, For the sake of your glorious name; Rescue us and forgive* our sins for the sake of your name. 10 Why should the nations say: “Where is their God?” Before our eyes may it become known among the nations That the shed blood of your servants has been avenged. 11 May you hear the sighing of the prisoner. Use your great power* to preserve* those sentenced to death.* 12 Repay our neighbors sevenfold For the taunts they have leveled at you, O Jehovah. 13 Then we, your people and the flock of your pasture, Will give thanks to you forever; And we will declare your praise from generation to generation.

To the director; set to “The Lilies.” A reminder. Of Aʹsaph. A melody. 80 O Shepherd of Israel, listen, You who are guiding Joseph just like a flock. You who sit enthroned above* the cherubs, Shine forth.*  2 Before Eʹphra·im and Benjamin and Ma·nasʹseh, Do stir up your mightiness; Come and save us.  3 O God, restore us; Let your face shine upon us, so that we may be saved.  4 Jehovah God of armies, how long will you be hostile toward* the prayer of your people?  5 You feed them tears as their bread, And you make them drink tears beyond measure.  6 You let our neighbors quarrel over us; Our enemies keep mocking us as they please.  7 O God of armies, restore us; Let your face shine upon us, so that we may be saved.  8 You made a vine depart from Egypt. You drove out the nations and planted it.  9 You cleared a space for it, And it took root and filled the land. 10 The mountains were covered by its shadow, And the cedars of God by its branches. 11 Its branches reached as far as the sea, And its shoots to the River.* 12 Why have you broken down the stone walls of the vineyard, So that all those passing by pluck its fruit? 13 The boars of the forest ravage it, And the wild animals of the field feed on it. 14 O God of armies, please return. Look down from heaven and see! Take care of this vine, 15 The stock* that your right hand has planted, And look upon the son whom* you made strong for yourself. 16 It is burned with fire, cut down. They perish at your rebuke.* 17 May your hand give support to the man at your right hand, To the son of man you have made strong for yourself. 18 Then we will not turn away from you. Preserve us alive, so that we may call on your name. 19 O Jehovah God of armies, restore us; Let your face shine upon us, so that we may be saved.

To the director; upon the Gitʹtith.* Of Aʹsaph. 81 Shout joyfully to God our strength. Shout in triumph to the God of Jacob.  2 Begin the music and take a tambourine, The melodious harp together with the stringed instrument.  3 Blow the horn on the new moon, On the full moon, for the day of our festival.  4 For it is a decree for Israel, A ruling of the God of Jacob.  5 He established it as a reminder for Joseph When He went out against the land of Egypt. I heard a voice* that I did not recognize:  6 “I lifted the burden from his shoulder; His hands were freed from the basket.  7 In your distress you called, and I rescued you; I answered you from the thundercloud.* I tested you at the waters of Merʹi·bah.* (Selah)  8 Hear, my people, and I will testify against you. O Israel, if you would only listen to me.  9 Among you, there will be no strange god, And you will not bow down to a foreign god. 10 I, Jehovah, am your God, The one who brought you out of the land of Egypt. Open your mouth wide, and I will fill it. 11 But my people did not listen to my voice; Israel would not submit to me. 12 So I let them follow their stubborn hearts; They did what they thought was right.* 13 If only my people would listen to me, If only Israel would walk in my ways! 14 Their enemies I would quickly subdue; I would turn my hand against their adversaries. 15 Those who hate Jehovah will cringe in his presence, And their outcome* will be forever. 16 But he will feed you* with the finest* wheat And satisfy you with honey from the rock.”

A melody of Aʹsaph. 82 God takes his place in the divine assembly;* In the middle of the gods* he judges:  2 “How long will you continue to judge with injustice And show partiality to the wicked? (Selah)  3 Defend* the lowly and the fatherless. Render justice to the helpless and destitute.  4 Rescue the lowly and the poor; Save them out of the hand of the wicked.”  5 They do not know, nor do they understand; They are walking about in darkness; All the foundations of the earth are being shaken.  6 “I have said, ‘You are gods,* All of you are sons of the Most High.  7 But you will die just as men do; And like any other prince you will fall!’”  8 Rise up, O God, and judge the earth, For all the nations belong to you.

A song. A melody of Aʹsaph. 83 O God, do not be silent; Do not keep quiet* or still, O Divine One.  2 For look! your enemies are in an uproar; Those who hate you act arrogantly.*  3 With cunning they secretly plot against your people; They conspire against your treasured ones.*  4 They say: “Come, let us annihilate them as a nation, So that the name of Israel may be remembered no more.”  5 They devise a unified strategy;* They have made an alliance* against you—  6 The tents of Eʹdom and the Ishʹma·el·ites, Moʹab and the Hagʹrites,  7 Geʹbal and Amʹmon and Amʹa·lek, Phi·lisʹti·a together with the inhabitants of Tyre.  8 As·syrʹi·a too has joined them; They give support to* the sons of Lot. (Selah)  9 Do to them as you did to Midʹi·an, As you did to Sisʹe·ra and Jaʹbin at the stream* of Kiʹshon. 10 They were annihilated at En-dor; They became manure for the ground. 11 Make their nobles like Oʹreb and Zeʹeb And their princes* like Zeʹbah and Zal·munʹna, 12 For they said: “Let us take possession of the land where God dwells.” 13 O my God, make them like a whirling thistle,* Like stubble blown about by the wind. 14 Like a fire that burns up the forest, Like a flame that scorches the mountains, 15 So may you pursue them with your tempest And terrify them with your windstorm. 16 Cover* their faces with dishonor, So that they may search for your name, O Jehovah. 17 May they be put to shame and be terrified forever; May they be disgraced and perish; 18 May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

For the director; upon the Gitʹtith.* Of the sons of Korʹah. A melody. 84 How lovely* your grand tabernacle is, O Jehovah of armies!  2 My whole being* yearns, Yes, I am faint with longing, For the courtyards of Jehovah. My heart and my flesh shout joyfully to the living God.  3 Even the bird finds a home there And the swallow a nest for herself, Where she cares for her young Near your grand altar, O Jehovah of armies, My King and my God!  4 Happy are those dwelling in your house! They continue to praise you. (Selah)  5 Happy are the men who find their strength in you, Whose hearts are set on the highways.  6 When they pass through the Baʹca Valley,* They make it into a place of springs; And the early rain clothes it* with blessings.  7 They will walk on from strength to strength; Each one appears before God in Zion.  8 O Jehovah God of armies, hear my prayer; Listen, O God of Jacob. (Selah)  9 Look, our shield and our God,* Look upon the face of your anointed one. 10 For a day in your courtyards is better than a thousand anywhere else! I choose to stand at the threshold of the house of my God Rather than to dwell in the tents of wickedness. 11 For Jehovah God is a sun and a shield; He gives favor and glory. Jehovah will not hold back anything good From those walking in integrity. 12 O Jehovah of armies, Happy is the man who trusts in you.

For the director. Of the sons of Korʹah. A melody. 85 You have shown favor, O Jehovah, to your land; You brought back those of Jacob who were taken captive.  2 You have pardoned the error of your people; You forgave* all their sin. (Selah)  3 You held back all your fury; You turned away from your hot anger.  4 Restore us,* O God of our salvation, And set aside your displeasure with us.  5 Will you be furious with us forever? Will you prolong your anger to generation after generation?  6 Will you not revive us again So that your people may rejoice in you?  7 Show your loyal love to us, O Jehovah, And grant us your salvation.  8 I will listen to what the true God Jehovah says, For he will speak peace to his people, to his loyal ones, But let them not return to overconfidence.  9 Surely his salvation is near to those who fear him, So that his glory may reside in our land. 10 Loyal love and faithfulness will meet together; Righteousness and peace will kiss each other. 11 Faithfulness will sprout from the earth, And righteousness will look down from the heavens. 12 Yes, Jehovah will give what is good,* And our land will yield its harvest. 13 Righteousness will walk before him And make a path for his footsteps.

A prayer of David. 86 Incline your ear,* O Jehovah, and answer me, For I am afflicted and poor.  2 Guard my life,* for I am loyal. Save your servant who is trusting in you, For you are my God.  3 Show me favor, O Jehovah, For I call to you all day long.  4 Make your servant* rejoice, For to you, O Jehovah, I turn.*  5 For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.  6 Listen, O Jehovah, to my prayer; And pay attention to my pleas for help.  7 I call on you in the day of my distress, For you will answer me.  8 There is none like you among the gods, O Jehovah, There are no works like yours.  9 All the nations that you made Will come and bow down before you, O Jehovah, And they will give glory to your name. 10 For you are great and do wondrous things; You are God, you alone. 11 Instruct me, O Jehovah, about your way. I will walk in your truth. Unify my heart* to fear your name. 12 I praise you, O Jehovah my God, with all my heart, And I will glorify your name forever, 13 For your loyal love toward me is great, And you have saved my life* from the depths of the Grave.* 14 O God, presumptuous men rise up against me; A band of ruthless men seek to take my life,* And they have no regard for you.* 15 But you, O Jehovah, are a God merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love and faithfulness.* 16 Turn to me and show me favor. Give your strength to your servant, And save the son of your slave girl. 17 Show me a sign* of your goodness, So that those who hate me may see it and be put to shame. For you, O Jehovah, are my helper and comforter.

Lit., “cover.”

Lit., “arm.”

Or possibly, “set free.”

Lit., “the sons of death.”

Or possibly, “between.”

Or “Reveal your radiance.”

Lit., “fume against.”

That is, the Euphrates.

Or “main stem of the vine.”

Or “branch that.”

Lit., “the rebuke of your face.”

See Glossary.

Or “language.”

Lit., “in the hidden place of thunder.”

Meaning “Quarreling.”

Lit., “They walked in their counsels.”

Lit., “time.”

Lit., “him,” that is, God’s people.

Lit., “the fat of.”

Or “in the assembly of the Divine One.”

Or “godlike ones.”

Or “Judge.”

Or “godlike ones.”

Or “keep speechless.”

Or “raise their heads.”

Lit., “concealed ones.”

Lit., “They consult with a heart together.”

Or “a covenant.”

Lit., “have become an arm to.”

Or “wadi.”

Or “leaders.”

Or “like tumbleweed.”

Lit., “Fill.”

See Glossary.

Or “deeply loved.”

Or “My soul.”

Or “the valley of baca bushes.”

Or possibly, “And the instructor enwraps himself.”

Or possibly, “Look at our shield, O God.”

Lit., “covered.”

Or “Gather us back.”

Or “prosperity.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or “soul.”

Or “the soul of your servant.”

Or “I raise my soul.”

Or “Give me an undivided heart.”

Or “soul.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “seek my soul.”

Or “have not set you in front of themselves.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “and truth.”

Or “evidence.”

^ (Ps. 83:0-18) A song. A melody of Aʹsaph. 83 O God, do not be silent; Do not keep quiet* or still, O Divine One.  2 For look! your enemies are in an uproar; Those who hate you act arrogantly.*  3 With cunning they secretly plot against your people; They conspire against your treasured ones.*  4 They say: “Come, let us annihilate them as a nation, So that the name of Israel may be remembered no more.”  5 They devise a unified strategy;* They have made an alliance* against you—  6 The tents of Eʹdom and the Ishʹma·el·ites, Moʹab and the Hagʹrites,  7 Geʹbal and Amʹmon and Amʹa·lek, Phi·lisʹti·a together with the inhabitants of Tyre.  8 As·syrʹi·a too has joined them; They give support to* the sons of Lot. (Selah)  9 Do to them as you did to Midʹi·an, As you did to Sisʹe·ra and Jaʹbin at the stream* of Kiʹshon. 10 They were annihilated at En-dor; They became manure for the ground. 11 Make their nobles like Oʹreb and Zeʹeb And their princes* like Zeʹbah and Zal·munʹna, 12 For they said: “Let us take possession of the land where God dwells.” 13 O my God, make them like a whirling thistle,* Like stubble blown about by the wind. 14 Like a fire that burns up the forest, Like a flame that scorches the mountains, 15 So may you pursue them with your tempest And terrify them with your windstorm. 16 Cover* their faces with dishonor, So that they may search for your name, O Jehovah. 17 May they be put to shame and be terrified forever; May they be disgraced and perish; 18 May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

Or “keep speechless.”

Or “raise their heads.”

Lit., “concealed ones.”

Lit., “They consult with a heart together.”

Or “a covenant.”

Lit., “have become an arm to.”

Or “wadi.”

Or “leaders.”

Or “like tumbleweed.”

Lit., “Fill.”